<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<msDescription id="Mh_17">
<msIdentifier>
<country reg="SE">Sweden</country>
<settlement>Lund</settlement>
<repository key="Mh">Lund University Library</repository>
<idno>Medeltidshandskrift 17</idno>
<altName type="former shelfmark">J 4:o 22</altName>
<altName type="former shelfmark">B. N. Mscr. 4:to N:o 38.</altName>
<altName type="database-identifier">scriptorium:Mh:113399:1129132218</altName>
</msIdentifier>
<msHeading>
  <title lang="ENG">National law of Magnus Eriksson</title> 
  <origPlace>Sweden</origPlace>
  <origDate notBefore="1347" notAfter="1400">14th century, late half (not before 1347)</origDate>
  <textLang langKey="SWE">Swedish</textLang>
 </msHeading>
<msContents>
<msItem n="1">
<locus from="1r" to="139r">ff. 1r-139r</locus>
<title type="uniform">Magnus Erikssons Landslag</title>
<title type="parallel" lang="ENG">National law of Magnus Eriksson</title>
<rubric>Hær byrias konongs balker mædh floccom</rubric>
<incipit>Um suerekes konongs riki huilkit sum i sik hauer syu biskupsdøme</incipit>
<explicit>oc þet uæri konongs <supplied>ensak</supplied></explicit>
</msItem>

<msItem n="2">
<locus from="139r" to="139r">f. 139r</locus>
<title type="uniform">Om edgång</title>
<title type="parallel" lang="ENG">On swearing an oath</title>
<incipit>Hwlkin som swer eedh oppa bok han swer edhen i triggia handha motthe</incipit>
<explicit>om jagh falsth sigher i tessom edh som mik är nw före lagd</explicit>
</msItem>


<msItem n="2.1">
<locus from="139v" to="139v">f. 139v</locus>
<title type="uniform">Om mened</title>
<title type="parallel" lang="ENG">On committing perjury</title>
<incipit>Hwlkin som falst swer oppa bok</incipit>
<explicit>til tess ath han haffwer scriptad (?) sigh och tagith oppenbara  bätringh</explicit>
</msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<support><p>Parchment</p></support><extent>ff. i (modern paper ) + 139 + i (modern paper)) <dimensions><height>200</height>145<width/></dimensions> mm.</extent>
<collation><p>18 quires: I: 6 (ff. 1-6), II: 8 (ff. 7-14), III: 8 (ff. 15-22), IV: 8 (ff. 23-30), V: 6 (ff. 31-36), VI: 8 (ff. 37-44), VII: 8 (ff. 45-52), VIII: 8 (ff. 53-60), IX: 8 (ff. 61-68), X: 8 (ff. 69-76), XI: 8 (ff. 77-84), XII: 8 (ff. 85-92), XIII: 8 (ff. 93-100), XIV: 8 (ff. 101-108), XV: 8 (ff. 109-116), XVI: 8 (ff. 117-124), XVII: 9 (ff. 125-133; f. 131 is inserted), XVIII: 6 (ff. 134-139). Catchwords in lower right margin of last leaf of every quire.</p></collation>
<layout columns="1" writtenLines="21"><p>One column; 21 written lines; ruled in ink; pricking in outer margins; written space: 140 x 90 mm.</p>
</layout>
<msWriting hands="1">
<handDesc script="textualis" medium="ink" scope="sole"><p>Textualis in one hand. Capital letters marked in red. In margins many juridical annotations in a 16th century cursive hand.</p></handDesc>
</msWriting> 

<decoration>
      <decoNote><p>A total of 26 pen flourished initials in red, blue and
	  towards the end also brown ink. One initial decorated with a human
	  face in profile. Occasional line fillings and simple marginal
	  decoration.</p> 
	<p>Three levels of initial decoration occur in the manuscript: the
	  lowest level is represented by the small monocoloured initials
	  beginning the capitula of each code ("balk"). They are of the same
	  heigth, 2-lines, and type as the lombards of the running text, with
	  restrained or sometimes omitted pen flourishing (on ff. 1r, 29r, 78v,
	  82r, 93r, 109r, 118r, 122r, 126v, 129r). The main text of each code
	  ("balk") begins with a large decorated 4-7-lines initial of the
	  middle level, in two or three colours with fillings of floral
	  ornaments and surrounded by pen flourishes. In the highest level,
	  represented by four initials, the pen flourishes extend beyond the
	  compartment of the letter, forming horizontal and vertical
	  borders. In the case of the first large initial, on f. 3r, the
	  decoration has been further heigthened by a denser character and the
	  adding of small birds.</p> 
	<p>Detailed description: f. <locus>3r</locus>: large intarsiated initial (E) of the
	  highest level in blue and red with void details in white, red
	  filigranated filling with blue dots, an outer rectangular area of
	  blue floral decoration with occasional red details, to the right
	  continuing in blue and red pen flourishing. The initial and the lower
	  part of the written text is surrounded, except for the right margin,
	  by blue and red lines and fifteen pen flourish ornaments alternating
	  in blue and red, nine of which are surmounted by small birds; f. <locus>21r</locus>:
	  large intarsiated initial (S) of the highest level in blue and red
	  with void details in white, filigranated filling in blue above and
	  red below and surrounded by red pen flourishing above and blue below,
	  continuing in red from the serifs towards the lower and outer edges;
	  f. <locus>29v</locus>: large initial (D) of the middle level in red and blue with
	  pen flourishing; f. <locus>35v</locus>: semilarge red initial (F) with a contour
	  drawing of a human face in profile continuing in a furry slim body
	  and ending with a fish tail; f. <locus>37r</locus>: large initial (F) of the highest
	  level in blue and red with filigranated filling, below red with blue
	  dots and above blue with red dots, pen flourishing in red extends in
	  diverging lines towards the lower and right edges; f. <locus>45r</locus>: in the
	  lower margin a drawing in red ink of a small bird sitting on top of a
	  heartshaped leaf; f. <locus>49v</locus>: large initial (U) of the highest level in
	  red and blue with filigranated filling in red consisting of an
	  ondulated stem with three flowers, the petals of which have details
	  in blue. The outer left contour of the initial is decorated with red
	  pen flourishing extending vertically and diverging below mid
	  page. The upper and right sides are decorated with pen flourishing in
	  blue extending horizontally from upper left with volutes and short
	  strokes suggesting an architectural structure corbel, certainly in
	  awarness of the content of the text, "bygningabalker"; f. <locus>79r</locus>: large
	  blue initial (N) of the middle degree with filigranated filling and
	  pen flourishing in red; f. <locus>83v</locus>: large initial (N) of the middle
	  degree in red and blue with filigranated filling in brown with red
	  details and outer pen flourishing in red; f. <locus>95r</locus>: large initial (R)
	  of the middle level in red and blue with red filigranated filling and
	  outer pen flourishing in brown and red; f. <locus>105v</locus>: large red initial
	  (M) of the middle level decorated with rows of white dots and
	  surrounded by blue pen flourishing; f. <locus>110v</locus>: large brown initial (N)
	  of the middle level with ondulating line, red floral filling and
	  surrounded by red pen flourishing: f. <locus>118v</locus>: large brown initial (N) of
	  the middle level with void leaf ornaments, red floral filling and
	  surrounded by red pen flourishing; f. <locus>122v</locus>: large blue initial (N) of
	  the middle level with void white ornaments, red floral filling and
	  surrounded by red pen flourishing; f. <locus>127r</locus>: large red initial (H) of
	  the middle level with intarsiated pattern, brown filigranated filling
	  and surrounded by brown pen flourishing; f. <locus>130v</locus>: large brown initial
	  S of the middle level with red filigranated filling and red pen
	  flourishing by a second, inferior, hand; f. <locus>130v</locus>: below, small red
	  initial (N) ending in a fish tail ornament.</p> 
	<p>Style: Well executed initials of a common version of the 14th
	  century Scandinavian synthesis of features from different north
	  european styles.</p> 
      </decoNote>
    </decoration>
    <bindingDesc>
      <binding>
	<p>Brown calfskin binding, Germany, Stuttgart 1967, singed with
	  a blue ink stamp on the inside of the lower cover: Restauriert Hans
	  Heiland &amp; Sohn. Size: 225 x 170 x 45 mm.</p> 
	<p>Brown calfskin binding over millboards. Two metal hook-clasp
	  fastenings with red leather straps at fore-edge (not from former
	  binding). Rounded spine. Tight back with four double raised
	  bands. Library code in pencil in the head compartment of the
	  back. Former edge trimming preserved. Plain single flyleaves and
	  pastedowns of paper.  Former shelf marks on front pastedown
	  (cfr. above). Also on front pastedown a note on Schlyter's
	  edition (cfr. bibliography) and a notation on the date of the
	  entrance of the manuscript in the library: <q>Inköpt 1751 se
	    consist. manualhandlingar 12/6 1751</q> and further down:
	  <q>1300-talets senare hälft</q>. In upper and lower left corners
	  the present shelf mark. Upper board  with preserved and restored
	  separate pastedown. All along sewing on four double cords laced
	  through the boards. The last textleaf of the bookblock with
	  restorations. Signed in blue ink stamp 1967 <q>Restauriert Hans
	    Heiland und Sohn</q> on the inside of the lower cover.</p>  
      </binding> 
    </bindingDesc>
    <foliation><p>Foliation in ink in upper right corner.</p></foliation>
    <additions><p>At f. 139r-v: Notes in a 16th century cursive script:
	<q>Hwlkin som swer eedh oppa bok ... och taghit oppenbara
	  bætringh</q>. Below on f. 139v in a later hand: <q>Fader
	  wår som æst i h.</q></p></additions> 
  </physDesc>
<history>
    <origin><p>Sweden, late 14th century (not before 1347).</p></origin>
    <provenance><p>In the 17th century the manuscript was owned by Nils
	Stackelberg, minister in charge of Estonian affairs (=lantråd i
	Estland) of Hjälmarsnäs, Mödders and Raggafer in
	Närke whose name appears in the upper margin of
	f. 1r. On f. <locus>109r</locus> another note of ownership
 (?).</p></provenance> 
    <acquisition><p>The manuscript was bought (with Medeltidshandskrift 16 and
	19) in 1751 from Johan Nelander, 1743-1782, professor of philosophy at
	the university of Lund (cfr. Cons. maj. manualhandliungar June 22,
	1751.</p></acquisition> 
  </history>
<additional>
<adminInfo>
<recordHist>
<source>
<p>Catalogued by Margarete Andersson-Schmitt; the manuscript description encoded in May of 2002 by Eva Nilsson Nylander.</p>
</source>
<change>
<date rend="creation">2005-10-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record uploaded</item>
</change>
<change>
<date rend="revision">2005-10-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record revised</item>
</change>
</recordHist>
<remarks rend="audience">
<p>external</p>
</remarks>
</adminInfo>
<listBibl>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Konung Magnus Erikssons Landslag</title>
<editor>Schlyter, C., J.</editor>
<title level="s">Samling af Sweriges Gamla Lagar</title>
<biblScope type="volume">10</biblScope>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Lund</pubPlace>
<date>1862</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope type="pages">pp. xiv-xv where it appears as manuscript N</biblScope>
</bibl>


<bibl>
<author>Geete, R.</author>
<title level="m">Fornsvensk bibliografi. Förteckning öfver Sveriges medeltida bokskatt på modersmålet samt därtill hörande litterära hjälpmedel</title>
<title level="s">SFSS</title>
<biblScope type="volume"/>
<imprint><pubPlace>Stockholm</pubPlace><date>1903</date></imprint><biblScope>nr. 406</biblScope>
</bibl>

<bibl>
<author>Åström, P.</author>
<title level="m">Senmedeltida svenska lagböcker. 136 lands- och stadslagshandskrifter. Dateringar och problem</title>
<title level="s">Acta Universitatis Stockholmiensis. Stockholm Studies in Scandinavian Philology. New Series.</title>
<biblScope type="volume">32</biblScope>
<imprint><pubPlace>Stockholm</pubPlace><date>2003</date></imprint><biblScope> passim and esp. pp. 220 and 224</biblScope>
</bibl>



</listBibl>
</additional>
</msDescription>
