<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 

<msDescription id="Mh_14" status="frag">
 <msIdentifier>
  <country reg="SE">Sweden</country>
  <settlement>Lund</settlement>
  <repository>Lund University Library</repository>
  <idno>Medeltidshandskrift 14</idno>
  <altName lang="LAT" type="nickname">Liber Scolae Virginis</altName>
 </msIdentifier>

 <msHeading>
  <title lang="ENG">Sequentiary</title> 
  <origPlace>Denmark (Lund)</origPlace>
  <origDate notBefore="1300" notAfter="1499">14th-16th century</origDate>
  <textLang langKey="LAT">Latin</textLang>
 </msHeading>

 <physDesc>
  <support><p>parchment and paper</p></support>
  <extent>ff. i + 20 + i +
      39<dimensions><height>300</height><width>220</width></dimensions>mm.</extent> 
    <bindingDesc><binding><p>Size: 327 x 255 x 30 mm. Brown goatskin binding
	  over millboards. Calf skin cover from former binding, contemporary
	  with manuscript, preserved on the new covering. Two long-strap
	  fastenings at fore-edge. (Former binding with only one fastening at
	  fore-edge according to documentation). Upper cover with five metal
	  bosses and lower cover with one central metal boss all in the shape
	  of a four petal flower. (The bosses are partly restored and only five
	  of eight bosses preserved, some of the bosses are misplaced compared
	  to photo documentation of former binding). Rounded spine. Tight back
	  with four raised double bands. Former edge trimming preserved. Creme
	  coloured paper pastedowns. All along sewing on four double cords
	  laced through the boards. Textblock restored and with five additional
	  quires of paper at the end of the textblock. Photographic
	  documentation of former binding and description of the rebinding
	  mounted on pastedown of the lower cover, signed by Hans Heiland
	  1964. Preserved leather fragment and bosses, contemporary with
	  manuscript, rebinding Germany, Stuttgart 1964.</p></binding> 
</bindingDesc>
</physDesc>

<additional>
<listBibl><bibl>
<author>Hammerich, A.</author>
<title level="m">Musik-minnesmaerker fra Middelalderen i Danmark</title>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Köbenhavn</pubPlace>
<date>1912</date>
<biblScope type="pages">pp. 41-69</biblScope>
</imprint>
</bibl>
</listBibl>
  </additional>
</msDescription>
