<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<msDescription id="Mh_27">
<msIdentifier>
<country reg="SE">Sweden</country>
<settlement>Lund</settlement>
<repository key="Mh">Lund University Library</repository>
<idno>Medeltidshandskrift 27</idno>
<altName type="former shelfmark">Ms. H. L. a) 4:o 36</altName>
<altName type="former shelfmark">Bibliotheca recentior N:o 6</altName>
<altName type="database-identifier">scriptorium:Mh:358719:1138806802</altName>
</msIdentifier>
<msHeading>
    <author>Vergilius</author>
    <title type="supplied" lang="ENG">Collected works</title> 
    <origPlace>Northern Italy</origPlace>
    <origDate notBefore="1460" notAfter="1480">15th century
      (1460-1480)</origDate> 
    <textLang langKey="LAT">Latin</textLang> 
  </msHeading>
<msContents>
<msItem n="1" defective="no"><locus from="1r" to="14r">ff. 1r-14r</locus>
<author>Publius Vergilius Maro</author>
<title type="uniform" lang="LAT">Bucolica</title>
<rubric>Publi Vergilii Maronis liber bucholicorum feliciter incipit</rubric>
<rubric type="final">Explicit liber bucholicorum Virgilii maronis</rubric>
</msItem>

<msItem n="2" defective="no">
<locus from="14r" to="49v">ff. 14r-49v</locus>
<author>Publius Vergilius Maro</author>
<title type="uniform">Georgica</title>
<rubric>Publi Virgilii maronis liber georgicorum feliciter incipit</rubric>
<note>Cum argumentis Ps. Ovidii; book 1: ff.14r-22r; book 2: ff.22r-30v; book 3: ff.31r-39v; book 4: ff.40r-48v.</note>
</msItem>

<msItem n="3">
<locus from="49r" to="49v">f. 49r-v</locus>
<title type="uniform">Anthologia latina</title>
<note>Lines 1-7 = Anthologia latina 672a; lines 19-31 = Anthologia latina 634; f. 50: blank.</note>
</msItem>

<msItem n="4" defective="no">
<locus from="51r" to="207v">ff. 51r-207v</locus>
<author>Publius Vergilius Maro</author>
<title type="uniform">Aeneidos</title>
<rubric>Publi Vergilii Maronis liber primus Aenaeidos feliciter incipit</rubric>
<rubric type="final">Publi virgilii maronis liber ultimus eneidos feliciter explicit.</rubric>
</msItem>


<msItem n="5">
<locus from="207v" to="208r">ff. 207v-208r</locus>
<title type="uniform">Anthologia latina 672</title>
</msItem>

<msItem n="6">
<locus from="208r" to="209v">f. 208r-209v (line 15)</locus>
<title type="uniform">Anthologia latina 507-518; 555-556</title>
<rubric>Epitaphium Virgilii maronis</rubric>
<rubric type="final">Explicit epythaphium Virgilii habens versus lxxiiii. Finis.</rubric>
</msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
    <support><p>Parchment.</p></support><extent>ff. i + 209 + i,
      <dimensions><height>253</height><width>170</width></dimensions>
      mm.</extent>

    <collation><p>21 quires: I: 10 (ff. 1-10), II: 10
	  (ff. 11-20), III: 10 (ff. 21-30), IV: 10 (ff. 31-40), V: 10
	  (ff. 41-50), VI: 10 (ff. 51-60), VII: 10 (ff. 61-70), VIII: 10
	  (ff. 71-80), IX: 10 (ff. 81-90), X: 10 (ff. 91-100), XI: 10
	  (ff. 101-110), XII: 10 (ff. 111-120), XIII: 10 (ff. 121-130), XIV: 8
	  (ff. 131-138), XV: 12 (ff. 139-150), XVI: 10 (ff. 151-160), XVII: 10
	  (ff. 161-170), XVIII: 10 (ff. 171-180), XIX: 10 (ff. 181-190), XX: 10
	  (ff. 191-200), XXI: 9 (ff. 201-209); the last quire is a quinion with
	  its last leaf cut out. Quire signatures, sometimes cropped,
	in the lower right corner of the recto of the first 5 leaves of each
	quinion (aai-v; bbi-v etc.). Decorated catchwords at the end of each
	quire, except in the 5th, where ff. 50r-v are blank.</p></collation>

    <layout columns="1" writtenLines="32"><p>One column; framed with a hard
	point, ruled in ink; 33 ruled lines, 32 written; ruled space: 170 x 100
	mm.</p>

    </layout>
    <msWriting hands="1">
      <handDesc script="humanistic book script" medium="ink" scope="sole"><p>
	  One hand; humanistic book script.</p></handDesc>
    </msWriting> 

    <decoration>
      <decoNote><p>Three illuminated and historiated, partly gilt initials with
	  illuminated and partly gilt foliate borders, 12 large decorated
	  initials, two semilarge decorated blue initials with surrounding
	  field with void floral or geometric pattern on red ground (ff. 22r,
	  31r) and 34 small pen flourished initials alternately blue with red
	  pen flourishes and red with violet pen flourishes, characterized by
	  the diagonally extended loops (ff. <locus>2r</locus>, <locus>3v</locus>, <locus>5r</locus>, <locus>6r</locus>, <locus>7v</locus>, <locus>9r</locus>, <locus>10r</locus>, <locus>11v</locus>,
	  <locus>12v</locus>, <locus>14r</locus>, <locus>14v</locus>, <locus>17v</locus>, <locus>22r</locus>, <locus>30v</locus>, <locus>39v</locus>, <locus>49r</locus> X 3, <locus>49v</locus>, <locus>63r</locus>, <locus>75r</locus>, <locus>86v</locus>, <locus>98r</locus>,
	  <locus>111v</locus>, <locus>126r</locus>, <locus>139r</locus>, <locus>150v</locus>, <locus>163v</locus>, <locus>178r</locus>, <locus>192v</locus>, <locus>207v</locus> X 2, <locus>208r</locus> X 2).</p>

	<p>Detailed description: f. <locus>1r</locus>: Illuminated and historiated initial (T)
	  against a background of burnished gold, with seated young male figure
	  to the left, dressed in a yellow tunic with red shades, blowing the
	  bagpipe in a pastoral environement including five sheep. The
	  symmetrically designed letter in pinkish red is decorated with star
	  ornaments and lines in white, the stem and the elongated, downwards
	  extended, ends of the top horisontal all end at the same level in
	  blue curling leaf ornaments. From the left corners of the initial's
	  framework leaves in green and pinkish red turning around themselves
	  extend into an illuminated foliate border on three sides in pink,
	  blue, red and gold, incorporating a waterbird on top, and a
	  butterfly, a parrot and the coat of arms of the Venetian Barbarigo
	  family in a green wreath of laurel with attached red ropes in the bas
	  de page; f. <locus>14r</locus>: Illuminated and historiated initial (Q) against a
	  background of burnished gold, with a young man dressed in a gilt
	  short tunic and red hoses mowing crop in a green landscape with a
	  yellow hill in the backdrop, a blue sky and a border inside the
	  letter of a white line and dots and a gilt band, inside the body of
	  the letter which is pinkish red, with calligraphic arabesque
	  decoration in white, one red leaf ornament extending into  the bottom
	  right corner and three smaller green leaf ornaments in the other
	  corners of the letter's framework. From the bottom left corner a
	  green and red leaf twisting around itself continues downwards into an
	  illuminated foliate border in left margin and lower margin, partly
	  with acanthus frieze, remaning part with thistle and flowers; f. <locus>40r</locus>:
	  Large blue initial (P) with surrounding field of intarsiated panels
	  with void ornaments against an alternating green and gold ground, red
	  outside the curvature of the letter; f. <locus>51r</locus>: Illuminated historiated
	  initial (A) against background of burnished gold, with a soldier in a
	  light ochre decorated armour, holding a spear and a pinkish red
	  shield against a blue background, standing on a green field with thin
	  yellow strokes, in front of the horisontal of the A which is a
	  separate green band with yellow details, thickening to the left and
	  loosely curling around the staple as a fluttering flag. The left stem
	  is a pinkish red bow with arabesque calligraphic decoration in white
	  to the right and a segmented border with white dots to the left,
	  ending at the bottom in a curling green leaf ornament, at the top in
	  a blue leaf turning around the top horisontal. The right stem is
	  straight, pinkish red with star ornaments and lines in white, ending
	  in two symmetrical blue curling leaf ornaments at the bottom, and
	  tightly curling in blue around the horisontal at the top. The top
	  horisontal is designed as an organic twig, bare to the right
	  thickening at the left into a large decorative leaf in green and
	  pinkish red with details in yellow, white and black, turning around
	  itself upwards and ending in a knob from which the thin stems of the
	  illuminated foliate border are spreading into three sides with
	  thistle, cornflower and other flowers in red, pink ad blue, inhabited
	  on top right by a butterfly, and at the bottom by a green parrot;
	  f. <locus>63r</locus>: Large blue initial (C) with void pattern, spiral in the
	  middle against green and gold, in the outer corners, void
	  filigranated pattern on red ground; f. <locus>75v</locus>: Large blue initial (P)
	  with void pattern, spiral in the middle against green and gold, in
	  the outer corners, void filigranated pattern on red ground; f. <locus>87r</locus>:
	  Large intarsiated blue initial (A) with void pattern on green and
	  gold, in the outer corners, void filigranated pattern on red ground;
	  f. <locus>98r</locus>: Large blue initial (I) with two void spirals against green,
	  gold and red; f. <locus>112r</locus>: Large intarsiated blue initial (S) against a
	  background with void floral pattern on green, gold and red and
	  filigranated pattern against red; f. <locus>126r</locus>: Large blue initial (T)
	  against filigranated void pattern on green and gold; f. <locus>139r</locus>: Large
	  blue initial (U) against filigranated void filigranated pattern on
	  green and gold and against red outside the letter; f. <locus>150v</locus>: Large
	  blue initial (U) against filigranated void spiral pattern on green
	  and gold; f. <locus>163v</locus>: Large blue initial (P) against void star pattern
	  on green and gold and filigranated pattern against red in corners;
	  f. 178r: Large blue initial (O) against filigranated void pattern on
	  green, red and gold; f. <locus>192r</locus>: Small red initial (E) with symmetrical
	  profuse pen work in red; f. <locus>192v</locus>: Large blue initial (T) against void
	  floral pattern on green, red and gold.</p>

	<p>Style: Both figure style and the disposition of elements in the
	  decorative borders are coherent with high quality Venetian and
	  Ferrarese illumination from the middle of the 15th century, but with
	  certain reactionary features as the gothic leaf-sprays pointing to an
	  early face in the development. The smaller pen flourished initials
	  show a controlled artificial version of renaissance lettering with
	  rows of circular ornaments inside the body of the letter clinging to
	  the parallell strokes continuing into the flourishes. The semilarge
	  and large initials with their panelled decoration can be compared to
	  display script from many north Italian centres of high quality. The
	  foliate borders are closely reminescent of Ferrarese work but are
	  more sparsely constructed and less confined to a disciplined
	  border-appearance than the Ferrarese counterparts, although close
	  relatives are found in the early works of Giorgio d'Allemagna and
	  Guglielmo Giraldi such as the Virgil made in 1458 for the venetian
	  ambassador to Ferrara, Leonardo Sanudo (Paris, BN, Ms. 7939 A), and
	  the somewhat earlier manuscript of "La Spagna in rima", (Ferrara,
	  Bibl. Communale Ariostea, Ms. II 132), illuminated by Giorgio
	  d'Allemagna for Borso d'Este. The Ferrarese elements cannot be
	  denied, but must be regarded as important influences on an early phase
	  of the Venetian book illumination rather than a Ferrarese origin. The
	  composition of the illuminated initials with a segmented and dotted
	  border along the red edge on f. <locus>51r</locus>, and on the green curling leaves,
	  imitative of pearl-rows, the twist of the leaf around the top
	  horisontal, the loosely tied flag-end of the horisontal on f. <locus>51r</locus>,
	  the use of ornamentation and colours, the disposition of flowers in
	  oblique angles within the foliage of the frame which is rythmically
	  ondulating rather than covering, together with a round-faced,
	  red-cheeked and rather serene figure-style, all occur in the same
	  combination in the work of Leonardo Bellini, to whom the
	  illuminations of Medeltidshandskrift 27 now are attributed. (For
	  Leonardo Bellini see: G. Mariani Canova, La Miniatura Veneta del
	  Rinascimento 1450 - 1500, Venezia 1969, pp. 22-24, 103-104, 142-144;
	  Ulrike Bauer-Eberhardt, "Die Rothschild-Miscellanea in Jerusalem,
	  Hauptwerk des Leonardo Bellini", Pantheon XLII/III, München
	  1984, pp. 229-237). The shape of the coat of arms is repeated in the
	  Lactantius Ms., the posture, with exaggerated contraposto, and the
	  armour of Aeneas is closely related to the figure of the archangel
	  Michael in the Oxford breviary, Oxford, Bodl. Libr.,
	  Ms. Canon. Liturg. 371, f. 7r. The general appearance of the figures,
	  folds and faces can be found througholut The Rothschild Miscellany
	  (Jerusalem, Israel Museum, Ms. 180/51) from c. 1470. The foliated
	  borders with flowers depicted in oblique angles in a sparse,
	  ondulating flow, can be seen above all in the two manuscripts
	  mentioned and the Copia della Promissione di Antonio Venier (Venezia,
	  Bibl. Marciana, Ms. Lat. X, 190) from c. 1458, whereas in his later
	  works the ornamental borders tend to stiffen and get more
	  crowded. Medeltidshandskrift 27 is here considerred to be
	  contemporary with the Bible, Venezia, Bibl. Marciana, Ms. Lat. I, 16,
	  dated by the scribe 1457, the Lactantius manuscript, Venezia,
	  Bibl. Marciana, Ms. Lat. II, 75, also dated by the scribe to 1457,
	  Oxford, Bodl. Libr., Ms. Canon. Liturg. 371, which Ulrike
	  Bauer-Eberhardt ascribed to Leonardo Bellini's own hand and dated it
	  close to the Lactantius Ms. (c. 1457). Close affinities are also
	  found on a separate leaf from a Venetian confraternity in the
	  collection of a Paris dealer, dated in the text to 1443. There is
	  reason to beleive that the date is referring to the scuola itself
	  rather than to the manuscript, which is more likely to be dated
	  around 1455-60.</p>

	<p>Iconography: The seated figure playing the bagpipe in the
	  historiated initial (T) on f. <locus>1r</locus> is identified by the illustrated
	  text itself "Tityre, tu patulae recubans..." and later "et ipsum
	  ludere quae vellem calamo permisit agresti." as the shepherd Tityrus,
	  the alter ego of Virgil and a self evident motif in this context. The
	  choice of musical instrument has been subject to some variation in
	  the virgilian iconography. Tityrus playing the bagpipe occurs
	  otherwise e.g. in the Omnia opera, printed by Bartlomeo de'Zanni in
	  Venice 1510, and in the ms. Reg. Lat. 1988 (f. 1r) of the Vatican
	  Library, probably illuminated in Rome c. 1456-58 and can be seen as a
	  more rustic approach to the text. The figure in the initial (Q) on
	  f. <locus>14r</locus> depicts the anonymous peasant tending to his soil described in
	  the first book of Georgics "who grazes down his luxuriant crop in the
	  young blade, soon as the growing corn is even with the furrow's top."
	  The armed soldier in the initial A on f. <locus>51r</locus> illustrates the opening
	  line of the Aeneid "Arma virumque" depicting Aeneas standing in
	  solitude, freed from the narrative.</p></decoNote>

    </decoration>

    <bindingDesc>
      <binding>
	<p>Blind- and gold-tooled brown goatskin binding, preserved decorated
	  covers northern Italy contemporary with the manuscript, small
	  restoration of the covers possibly 18th century. Rebinding Sweden
	  20th century. Size: 260 x 180 x 55 mm.</p>
	<p>Brown goatskin binding over square edged wooden boards. Rebinding
	  with new back and covers from former binding preserved, covering
	  material in part restored on both covers. Four engraved metal
	  hook-clasp fastenings with ornamental nails (catch plates, straps and
	  some nails missing). Five metal bosses on each cover. Tight back with
	  three double raised bands. Embroidered endbands of beige linen. Gilt
	  edges. Single flyleaves and pastedowns of parchment. Pastedowns from
	  former binding preserved as separated pastedowns. On front pastedown:
	  2 former shelf marks (cfr. above), a donation note in the hand of
	  G. Sommelius (1767-99; cfr. below) and further down the owner's name
	  crossed out. There is also the figure <q>3</q> in the same ink as the
	  note. On back pastedown there is a note only partially legible (a
	  verse from the Aeneid?). All along sewing on three double cords laced
	  through the boards.</p> 
	<p>The covers are blind-tooled with a border of two triple fillets
	  and several panels of multiple blind fillets. The outer panel
	  shows a repeated rectangular abstract tool. The mitred centre
	  panel is tooled with an over-all design of twisted rope enclosing
	  a rectangular centrepiece with an eight-pointed star. Gilt
	  roundels "alla fiorentina" are scattered over the
	  design. (cfr. Hobson 1989, p. 19
	  sqq.).</p>
      </binding>
    </bindingDesc> 

    <foliation><p>Foliated in pencil by modern cataloguer in upper right
	corner.</p></foliation>

  </physDesc>
<history>
    <origin><p>Northern Italy, 1460-1480. The manuscript was produced for a
	member of the Barbarigo family in Venice as shown by the worn coat of
	arms on f. 1r. Several other mss. belonging to other members of the
	same family are known: Wien, Bibl. nat. 39 of 1456, also Virgil, made
	for Girolamo Barbarigo; two mss. from the Royal Library in Copenhagen
	described by Ellen Joergensen in Catalogus codicum latinorum medii aevi
	Bibliothecae Regiae Hafniensis, Hafniae 1926, p. 296  (Koebenhavn, KB,
	Ny kgl. S. 214:b 4to) and p. 385 (Koebenhavn, KB, Gl. kgl. S. 1928 4to)
	with reproductions of the coats of arms (pl. VI. 5). There is at
	present no way of telling which member of the influential ducal family
	was the owner of Medeltidshandskrift 27. Chronologically both doges
	Marco d. 1486 and Agostino d. 1501 are possible candidates, as is
	Daniele Barbarigo, the owner of other manuscripts in Copenhagen and
	Vienna, Wien, UB, Cod. Ser. n. 26030 (olim I 528397 [Ms I 978]), dated
	1463, and Girolamo Barbarigo d. 1501, who was elected Capo del
	Consiglio dei Dieci in 1455. One could suspect connections between the
	Barbarigo family and the humanists Guarino da Verona and Leonardo
	Sanudo or his relative Lorenzo Sanudo, who comissioned both Guglielmo
	Giraldi, Giorgio d'Alemagna and Leonardo Bellini to illuminate
	manuscripts, including the Lactantius Ms. and the Virgil Ms. Paris, BN,
	Ms. 7939 A, thus indicating Lorenzo Sanudo as a probable source of
	acquisition. (cfr. Anselm Fremmer, Venezianische Buchkultur,
	Bücher, Buchhändler und Leser in der Frührenaissance,
	Köln 2001, pp. 158, 416 ff.).</p></origin>

    <acquisition><p>The manuscript was given to Lund University Library in 1713
	by <name type="person" role="owner">Andreas Rydelius
	  (1671-1738)</name>, professor of thelogy and 1734 bishop of
	Lund. Since Rydelius' library had burnt down in 1711 ("Allenast
	några fåå, som woro af prydno i främmande
	händer blefwo conserverade." cfr. Kilian Stobaeus, Parentation
	öfver A Rydelius, Samlingar till And. Rydelii Biografi 1, [p. 15])
	the book must have been acquired by Rydelius some time between 1711 and
	1713 when the donation note is dated (cfr. front paste down: <q>Andreas
	  Rydelius Philos. P. P. non minus suo erga remp. Academicam studio
	  quam lege impulsus, hunc operum Virgilii M. codicem manuscriptum olim
	  ex Germania in illustrem Bibliothecam Bannerianam inde se forte
	  delatum nunc in Bibliotheca publica Carolina reponit ibi ut optat
	  speratque errores tandem suos migrationesque terminaturum. Lunda
	  Gothorum, 8:va Iulii a.p.n. X. 1713.</q>). Rydelius bought it from
	<name>Johan Klasson Banér</name> (1659 - 1739), who in his turn
	had inherited it from <name>Johan Gabriel Banér</name> (1662 -
	1706), general in Holstein-Gottorp, and around 1704-05 several times
	offered the post as general of the republic of Venice. The manuscript
	could have been given to Banér by Giovanni Francesco Barbarigo
	(1658 - 1730) who had started his career as a diplomat, or by Pietro
	Barbarigo (1671-1725), patriarch of Venice in 1706, or by cardinal
	Marco Antonio Barbarigo (d. 1706), bishop of Corfu and book
	collector.</p></acquisition></history>
<additional>
<adminInfo>
<recordHist>
<source>
<p>Catalogued and encoded in December 2000 by Eva Nilsson Nylander.</p>
</source>
<change>
<date rend="creation">2006-02-01</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record uploaded</item>
</change>
<change>
<date rend="revision">2006-02-01</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record revised</item>
</change>
</recordHist>
<remarks rend="audience">
<p>external</p>
</remarks>
</adminInfo>
<listBibl>
<bibl>
<author>Dudik, B.</author>
<title level="m">Forschungen in Schweden fur Mährensgeschichte</title>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Brunn</pubPlace>
<date>1852</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope type="pages">pp. 367-368</biblScope>
</bibl>

<bibl>
<author>Ek, Joh., Gust.</author>
<title level="m">Ad Publium Virgilium Maronem ex codice membranaceo Biblioth. Acad. Lundensis nunc primum collato lectionis varietatem adnotavit Joh. Gust. Ek. (Accedunt observatiunculae criticae)</title>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Lundae</pubPlace>
<date>1847</date>
</imprint>
</bibl>

<bibl>
<author>Pellegrin, E.</author>
<title level="a">Manuscrits d'auteurs latins de l'époque classique conservés dans les bibliothèques publiques de Suède</title>
<title level="j">Bulletin d'information de l'institut de recherches et d'histoire des textes</title>
<biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
<date>1954</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope type="pages">pp. 7-32 (esp. pp. 28-31)</biblScope>
</bibl>
</listBibl>
</additional>
</msDescription>
