<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<msDescription id="Mh_33">
<msIdentifier>
<country reg="SE">Sweden</country>
<settlement>Lund</settlement>
<repository key="Mh">Lund University Library</repository>
<idno>Medeltidshandskrift 33</idno>
<altName type="database-identifier">scriptorium:Mh:549865:1137070806</altName>
</msIdentifier>
<msHeading>
      <title lang="ENG">Psalter</title> 
      <origPlace>Holland (Utrecht)</origPlace>
      <origDate notBefore="1500" notAfter="1525">16th century, early</origDate>
      <textLang langKey="DUT">Dutch</textLang>
    </msHeading>
<msContents>

      <msItem n="1">
	<locus from="3r" to="11v">ff. 3r-11v</locus>
	<title type="uniform">Calendar</title>
	<note><p>In red: Pancratius (12. 5), Gereon (10. 10), Willibrordus,
	    bishop of Utrecht (7. 11), Lebuinus (12. 11), indicating the
	    diocese of Utrecht</p> 
	  <p>Ff. 1r-2v: blank.</p> 
	</note>
      </msItem>

      <msItem n="2">
	<locus from="12r" to="14v">ff. 12r-14v</locus>
	<title type="uniform">Computistic tables, partially imcomplete</title>
	<note><p>On f. <locus>14r</locus>: tables; and on f. <locus>14v</locus>
	    a much later hand has added the outlines for a new table.</p> 
      </note> 

	<msItem n="2.1"><locus from="13r" to="13r">f. 13r</locus>
	  <incipit>Aries ist hoeft daer in is goet laeten</incipit>
	</msItem>

        <msItem n="2.2"><locus from="13v" to="13v">f. 13v</locus>
	  <title>Golden Numbers</title>
	  <incipit>Hij begint dat gulden ghetal ende die sondaeges
	    letter</incipit>
	</msItem>


    </msItem>

  <msItem n="3">
    <locus from="15r" to="214r">ff. 15r-214r</locus>
    <title type="uniform">Psalter</title>
    <incipit>Die sanck der psalmen hillighet dat lichaem</incipit>
    <explicit>alle geesten louet den louet den heren Hijr gaet de psalter wt
      ... Ende hijr begynnen de cantica ... .</explicit> 
    <note><p>According to Biemans, the translation is by Geert Groote and Johan
	Scutken.</p> 
      <p>On f. <locus>16r</locus>: <q>lof godes in sijnre herten
	  draeget</q>.</p>  
      <p>On f. <locus>16v</locus>: <q>Wilstu penitencie doen bichte van dinen
	  sonden</q>.</p> 
      <p>On f. <locus>18v</locus>: <q>Hijr begint als die leraers segghen een
	  boeck van den loeue godes</q>.</p> 
      <p>On f. <locus>21v</locus>: <q>Alsoe als sancte iheronimus secht in den
	  prologus opten solter</q>.</p> 
      <p>On f. <locus from="22r" to="22v">22r/v</locus>: <q>datmen vindet of
	  ghemeenlick of sonderlinghe</q>.</p> 
      <p>On f. <locus>22v</locus>: <q>Hijr begint die eerst psalm beatus vir
	  Dese psalm segghen die meisters  ...  Saelich is die man die niet of
	  ghegaen is ... </q> after which there is a lacuna of one leaf;
	f. <locus>23r</locus> starts with Ps. 2.</p> 

      <p>The Latin initia, rubricated, quoted for each psalm. After the end of
	each psalm there is information as to who has written it and on what
	occasion.</p> 
    </note>
  </msItem>

    <msItem n="4">
      <locus from="214r" to="228v">ff. 214r-228v</locus>
      <title type="uniform">Cantica</title>
      <rubric>Confiteor tibi</rubric>
      <incipit>Ic sal belijen here wantu my toernich biste</incipit>
      <explicit>soe en mach he niet beholden bliuen Amen Deo gracias</explicit>
      <note><p>Before each song information about origin; rubricated Latin
	  initia.</p><p>Ff. 229r-230v: blank.</p></note> 

      <msItem n="4.1"><locus from="214v" to="215r">ff. 214v-215r</locus>
	<rubric>Ego dixi</rubric>
	<incipit>Ic sprac int middel mynre daeghen</incipit>
      </msItem>

      <msItem n="4.2"><locus from="215v" to="216r">ff. 215v-216r</locus>
	<rubric>exultauit cor</rubric>
	  <incipit>Myn herte heuet vrolick ghewest</incipit></msItem>

      <msItem n="4.3"><locus from="f. 216v" to="217v">ff. 216v-217v</locus>
	  <rubric>cantemus</rubric>
	  <incipit>Synghe wy den heren want he is glorioselick
	  gheert</incipit>
      </msItem>

      <msItem n="4.4"><locus from="218r" to="219r">ff. 218r-219r</locus>
	<rubric>domine audiui</rubric>
	<incipit>Here ic hoerde din oren</incipit></msItem>

      <msItem n="4.5"><locus from="219v" to="222v">ff. 219v-222v</locus>
	<rubric>audite celi</rubric>
	<incipit>Hoert v hemelen dat ic spreken sal</incipit></msItem>

      <msItem n="4.6"><locus from="223r" to="223v">ff. 223r-223v</locus>
	<rubric>benedic</rubric>
	<incipit>Benediet den heren alle werke</incipit>
      </msItem>

      <msItem n="4.7"><locus from="224r" to="224r">ff. 224r</locus>
	<rubric>benedictus</rubric>
	<incipit>Ghebenedijt sy de here god van israel</incipit>
      </msItem>

      <msItem n="4.8"><locus from="224v" to="225r">ff. 224v-225r</locus>
	<rubric>te deum lau</rubric>
	<incipit>Dy god loue wy</incipit>
      </msItem> 

      <msItem n="4.9"><locus from="225v" to="226r">ff. 225v-226r</locus>
	<rubric>Magnificat anima</rubric>
	<incipit>Myne ziele maket groet den heren</incipit>
      </msItem> 

      <msItem n="4.10"><locus from="226r" to="226r">f. 226r</locus>
	<rubric>Nunc dimit[t]is domine</rubric>
	<incipit>Nu laet here dinen knecht nae dinen woerden in
	  vreden</incipit>
      </msItem> 

      <msItem n="4.11"><locus from="226v" to="226v">f. 226v</locus>
	<rubric>quicumque vult</rubric>
	<incipit>Soe we beholden wil wesen</incipit>
      </msItem>

    </msItem>

  </msContents>
<physDesc>
    <support><p>Paper.</p><watermarks><p>Watermarks,
	  visible e.g. at ff. 23 and 215-216 with the arms of Savoy and France
	  and a walking unicorn (very close to Briquet 1848), are probably
	  attributable to Chalons-sur-Marne around 1523.</p></watermarks> 
    </support>

    <extent>ff. 230,
      <dimensions><height>140</height><width>100</width></dimensions>
      mm.</extent> 
    <collation><p>Collation is uncertain since the manuscript
	has been rebound.; 28 quires: I: 12 (ff. 1-12), II: 11
	  (ff. 13-23), III: 6 (ff. 24-29), IV: 9 (ff. 30-38), V: 8 (ff. 39-46),
	  VI: 8 (ff. 47-54), VII: 8 (ff. 55-62), VIII: 8 (ff. 63-70; ff. 69 and
	  70 added), IX: 6 (ff. 71-76), X: 10 (ff. 77-86; originally a senion),
	  XI: 9 (ff. 87-95; f. 95 added), XII: 6 (ff. 96-101), XIII: 9
	  (ff. 102-110; originally a quinion), XIV: 9 (ff. 111-119; f. 119
	  added), XV: 7 (ff. 120-126; f. 126 added), XVI: 8 (ff. 127-134),
	  XVII: 8 (ff. 135-142), XVIII: 8 (ff. 143-150), XIX: 9 (ff. 151-159;
	  f. 159 added), XX: 6 (ff. 160-165), XXI: 10 (ff. 166-175), XXII: 6
	  (ff. 176-181), XXIII: 9 (ff. 182-190), XIV: 8 (ff. 191-198), XXV: 8
	  (ff. 199-206), XXVI: 8 (ff. 207-214), XXVII: 9 (ff. 215-223), XXVIII:
	  7 (ff. 224-230).</p></collation> 

    <layout columns="1" writtenLines="18"><p>One column; 18 written lines;
	ruled in ink; written space: 142 x 100 mm.</p> 
    </layout>
    <msWriting hands="1">
      <handDesc script="hybrida"><p>Main text in hybrida in one hand. Rubricated, often with instructions
	  to rubricator partiallly legible in cropped margins.</p></handDesc> 
    </msWriting> 

    <decoration>
      <decoNote><p>One illuminated and gilt three-sided frame
	    (f. <locus>172v</locus>), 8 
	  illuminated and gilt borders with flower decoration
	    (ff. <locus>53r</locus>, <locus>60v</locus>, 
	  <locus>90r</locus>, <locus>98r</locus>, <locus>109v</locus>,
	    <locus>118v</locus>, <locus>130v</locus>, <locus>154v</locus>), 25
	    large illuminated 3-6 lines 
	  initials with extended pen flourishes or otherwise emphasised
	  decoration (ff. <locus>15r</locus>, <locus>53r</locus>,
	    <locus>60v</locus>, <locus>82r</locus>, <locus>90r</locus>,
	    <locus>98r</locus>, <locus>109v</locus>, <locus>118v</locus>,
	    <locus>130v</locus>, <locus>132r</locus>, 
	  <locus>139v</locus>, <locus>149v</locus>, <locus>154v</locus>,
	    <locus>172v</locus>, <locus>179v</locus>, <locus>181v</locus>,
	    <locus>184v</locus>, <locus>187v</locus>, <locus>188v</locus>,
	    <locus>192r</locus>, <locus>197v</locus>, 
	  <locus>201v</locus>, <locus>219v</locus>, <locus>224v</locus>,
	    <locus>225v</locus>), 7 smaller, 3-4 lines, illuminated initials 
	  with rows of drops in the margin instead of pen flourishes
	    (ff. <locus>45r</locus>, 
	  <locus>70r</locus>, <locus>89r</locus>, <locus>163r</locus>,
	    <locus>183r</locus>, <locus>186r</locus>, <locus>223r</locus>), 15
	    lombards with void white, and 
	  occasional red details, often with incorporated simple drawings of
	  human faces in profile (ff. <locus>29v</locus>, <locus>33r</locus>,
	    <locus>39r</locus>, <locus>95v</locus>, <locus>175r</locus>,
	    <locus>176v</locus>, <locus>177r</locus>, 
	  <locus>180r</locus>, <locus>190v</locus>, <locus>191r</locus>,
	    <locus>193r</locus>, <locus>195r</locus>, <locus>200v</locus>,
	    <locus>208v</locus>, <locus>226v</locus>), and numerous simply 
	  decorated line fillers (e.g. ff. <locus>22v</locus>,
	    <locus>127r</locus>, <locus>135r</locus>, <locus>200v</locus>). On
	    f. <locus>13v</locus> a 
	  circular diagram in red on the golden numbers with two concentric
	  registers, two crosses and a rubric "Md" suggesting an approximate
	  date of the manuscript. The colours are applied in thin washes.</p> 

	<p>Detailed description: f. <locus>53r</locus>: initial (D) in blue and
	    orange with 
	  leaf ornaments in orange, yellow and green, floral filling in mauve,
	  blue, orange, green and gold against a yellow background, surrounding
	  field with multiple contours in brown. Border in upper  margin with
	  ondulating stem and small stars in gold, flower buds, or rather,
	  pumpkins in orange and mauve; f. <locus>60v</locus>: initial (U) in
	    blue with leaf 
	  ornaments in mauve, green and orange, void white fields filled with
	  red dots, decorative filling with leaf-ornaments against a background
	  in, green, orange and mauve. Surrounding field in green  and penwork
	  extending in leaf-ornamens and sprouts in dark red lines with details
	  in green. Border in upper margin with ondulating stem and small stars
	  in gold, zucchini or cucumbers in green, orange or mauve with flowers
	  in orange; f. <locus>90r</locus>: initial (D) in blue with (faded)
	    leaf-ornaments 
	  and floral filling in green, orange and mauve against a yellow
	  background. Surrounding field in brown and orange with multiple
	  contoursin brown. Border in upper margin with ondulating stem and
	  small stars in gold, small green leaves and three-leaf flowers in
	  orange, mauve and blue; f. <locus>98r</locus>: initial (H) in blue
	    with floral 
	  ornaments in mauve, blue and gold, floral filling in green, blue and
	  orange against a yellow background, surrounding multiple contours in
	  brown. Border in upper margin with ondulating stem and small stars in
	  gold, small green leaves and hop flowers in green and mauve;
	    f. <locus>109v</locus>: 
	  initial (G) in blue with floral ornaments in green, orange and gold,
	  floral filling in green, blue, mauve, orange and gold against a
	  yellow background, surrounding multiple contours in brown. Border in
	  upper margin with ondulating stem and small stars in gold, small
	  green leaves and pear-shaped flowers in blue, orange and mauve;
	  f. <locus>118v</locus>: initial (G) in blue with leaf ornaments in green and orange,
	  floral filling in dark red outline and orange against a green
	  background. Surrounding field in green and penwork extending in
	  leaf-ornamens and sprouts in dark red lines with details in
	  green. Border in upper margin with ondulating stem and small stars in
	  gold, small green leaves and strawberries in orange and mauve;
	  f. <locus>130v</locus>: initial (D) in blue with leaf ornaments in
	    green, floral 
	  filling in dark red outline and green against a background in green
	  and mauve. Surrounding field in green and mauve, and penwork
	  extending in leaf-ornamens and sprouts in dark red lines with details
	  in green. Border in lower margin with ondulating stem and small stars
	  in gold, large green thistle-leaves and flowers in mauve;
	    f. <locus>154v</locus>: 
	  initial (H) in blue with leaf ornaments in orange and mauve, floral
	  filling in dark red outline against a background in green and
	  mauve. Penwork with volutes and sprouts in dark red lines with
	  details in green. Border in upper margin with ondulating stem and
	  small stars in gold, small green leaves and thistle-flowers in mauve;
	  f. <locus>172v</locus>:  illuminated and gilt three-sided frame with
	    contours, 
	  ondulating stem and star ornaments in gold, blue, mauve and orange
	  flowers, small drop-shaped green leaves and a few larger leaves of
	  thistle or holly. Initial (D) in blue with floral decoration in mauve
	  and orange, floral filling in green, mauve, orange and blue with gilt
	  detail against a yellow backround, surrounding field in black and
	  yellow.</p> 

	<p>Style: The decoration belongs to the same Northern Dutch tradition
	  as e.g. Leiden, UB, Ltk 328, dated 1475, and Leiden, UB, Ltk 348, and
	  is somewhat similar to Leiden, UB, Bpl, 2843, (f. 208r) dated
	  1519.</p></decoNote> 
    </decoration>


    <bindingDesc>
      <binding><p>Blind-tooled brown sheepskin binding, preserved decorated
	  covers the Netherlands, contemporary with the manuscript. Rebinding,
	  Germany, Stuttgart, signed with an ink stamp at the inside of the
	  lower cover: <q>Restauriert Hans Heiland &amp; Sohn, 1963. Size: 150
	    x 115 x 48 mm.</q></p> 
	<p>Brown sheepskin binding over square edged wooden boards. Rebinding
	  with the covers from former binding preserved. Two hook clasp
	  fastenings at fore-edge, straps, anchor plates and nails new. Rounded
	  spine. Tight back with four raised bands. Blind-tooled library cloth
	  label at the tail of the back. Former edge trimming preserved. Two
	  plain flyleaves at the front, former parchment pastedowns preserved
	  as separate pastedowns. On the upper pastedown former shelf marks
	  (cfr. above) and present shelf mark in pencil, with notes in the hand
	  of Gustaf Sommelius, librarian at Lund University Library 1767-99, on
	  the contents: <q>Exegesis Psalmorum Davidis lingua germanica
	    antiqua</q>; in the upper left corner, in pencil: <q>h. 14.2,
	    br. 10 cm.</q> in the hand of librarian August Palm
	  (1826-1907). All along sewing on four raised cords laced through the
	  boards. Photograph of former binding inserted at lower cover.</p>  
	<p>The covers are blind-tooled to a frame and panel of parallel
	  vertical stripes made of a roll and double fillets. The roll shows a
	  four-petal flower within a lozenge.</p>
      </binding>
    </bindingDesc> 
    <foliation><p>Foliated in pencil by modern cataloguer in upper right
	corner; f. 231 is the lower pastedown; between f. 22 and 23 there is
	one folio that had a large initial facing f. 22v
	missing.</p></foliation>

    <additions><p>At f. 15r in upper margin: <q>Om frede ende enicheit</q>;
	from f. 31r numbers and notes in the margins referring to the text, in
	the hand of August Palm, librarian at Lund University Library
	1856-1907.</p></additions>

    <condition><p>From f. 175 the paper is damaged by humidity but the text
	remains legible. </p></condition>

  </physDesc>
<history>
    <origin><p>Holland (Utrecht), early 16th century.</p></origin>

    <provenance><p>The mannuscript was apparently owned by Gosen Conders,
	possibly a nun, cfr. note on lower pastedown: <q>s[uster?] gosen
	  conders.</q> Biemans (1984) erroneously reads "couders" instead of
	"conders". Gosen may well be identical with the Gosen Conders who owned
	Leiden UB, Ltk. 285.</p></provenance> 
    <acquisition><p>It was acquired by Lund University Library ab. 1750,
	cfr. note on upper pastedown: 1746 N. I.</p></acquisition> 
  </history>
<additional>
<adminInfo>
<recordHist>
<source>
<p>Catalogued by Margarete Andersson-Schmitt, the
	    manuscript description encoded in August, 2002 by Eva Nilsson
	    Nylander.</p>
</source>
<change>
<date rend="creation">2006-01-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record uploaded</item>
</change>
<change>
<date rend="revision">2006-01-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record revised</item>
</change>
</recordHist>
<remarks rend="audience">
<p>external</p>
</remarks>
</adminInfo>
<listBibl>
<bibl>
<author>Biemans, J.A.A.M.</author>
<title level="m">Middelnederlandse Bijbelhandschriften, Leiden 1984 (= Verzameling van Middelnederlandse Bijbelteksten. Catalogus)</title>
<imprint><pubPlace>Leiden</pubPlace>
<date>1984</date></imprint>
<biblScope type="pages">pp. 117-118: n. 83 (older bibliography quoted here).</biblScope>
</bibl>
<bibl>
<author>Borchling, C.</author>
<title level="a">Mittelniederdeutsche Handschriften in Skandinavien, Schleswig-Holstein, Mecklenburg un Vorpommern. Zweiter Reisebericht</title>
<title level="j">Nachrichten von Königl. Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften zu Göttingen. Philologisch-historische Klasse 1900. Beiheft</title>
<biblScope type="volume"/>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Göttingen</pubPlace>
<date>1900</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope type="pages">pp. 1-204 (p. 137)</biblScope>
</bibl>
<bibl>
<author>Kernkamp, G. W.</author>
<title level="m">Verslag van een onderzoek in Zweden, Noorwegen en Denemarken naar archivalia, belangrijk voor de geschiedenis van Nederland</title>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>s'Gravenhage</pubPlace>
<date>1903</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope type="pages">p. 3</biblScope>
</bibl>
<bibl>
<author>Rooth, E</author>
<title level="a">Medelnederländska trubadurdikter funna i Universitetsbiblioteket i Lund</title>
<title level="j">Nordisk tidskrift för Bok- och Biblioteksväsen</title>
<biblScope type="volume">14</biblScope>
<imprint>
<date>1927</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope type="pages">pp. 142-146 (p. 143)</biblScope>
</bibl>
<bibl>
<author>Vreese, W. de</author>
<title level="a">Sint Augustinus in het Middelnederlandsch. Uit de Bibliotheca Neerlandica Manuscripta</title>
<title level="m">Miscellanea Augustiniana. Gedenkboek samengesteld uit verhandelingen over S. Augustinus bij de viering van zijn zalig overlijden voor 15 eeuwen CDXXX-MCMXXX</title>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>[Rotterdam]</pubPlace>
<date>1930</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope type="pages">pp. 341-373 (p. 363)</biblScope>
<note>
reprint in: Over handschriften en handschriftenkunde: tien codicologische
	  studiën, bijeengebracht, ingeleid en toegelicht door
	  P. J. H. Vermeeren, Zwolle 1962 (= Zwolse Reeks van Taal- en
	  Letterkunde 11), pp. 85-115 (p. 106).</note>
</bibl>
</listBibl>
</additional>
</msDescription>
