<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<msDescription id="Mh_38">
<msIdentifier>
<country reg="SE">Sweden</country>
<settlement>Lund</settlement>
<repository key="Mh">Lund University Library</repository>
<idno>Medeltidshandskrift 38</idno>
<altName type="nickname" lang="LAT">Breviarium Turonense</altName>
<altName type="database-identifier">scriptorium:Mh:983003:1127467851</altName>
</msIdentifier>
<msHeading>
    <title lang="ENG">Breviary</title>
    <origPlace>France (Tours)</origPlace>
    <origDate notBefore="1450" notAfter="1500">15th century, later half</origDate>
    <textLang langKey="LAT">Latin</textLang>
    <note>
      <p>For use in the convent of St. Julian de Tours.</p><p>Type B.</p></note> 
  </msHeading>
<msContents>
<msItem n="1">
<locus from="2r" to="7v">ff. 2r- 7v</locus>
<title type="uniform">Calendar</title></msItem>

<msItem n="2">
<locus from="8r" to="138v">ff. 8r-138v</locus>
<title type="uniform">Temporale, winter part</title>
<rubric>dominica prima in adventu domini</rubric>
<incipit>Ecce dies veinunt [sic!] dicit dominus</incipit>
<explicit>Mulieres sedentes ad monumentum lamentabantur flentes dominum</explicit>
</msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
    <support><p>Parchment</p></support> <extent>ff. ii (paper) + 138
      ii (paper)<dimensions><height>175</height><width>120</width></dimensions>mm.
    </extent>
<collation><p>18 quires: I: 8 (ff. 1-7); II: 8 (ff. 8-15); III: 8 (ff. 16-23); IV: 8 (ff. 24-31); V: 7 (ff. 32-38; f. 38 is added); VI: 8 (ff. 39-46); VII: 8 (ff. 47-54); VIII: 8 (ff. 55-62); IX: 8 (ff. 63-70; ff. 64, 69 and ff. 64, 68 are not conjugate); X: 8 (ff. 71-78); XI: 8 (ff. 79-86); XII: 8 (ff. 87-94); XIII: 8 (ff. 95-102); XIV: 8 (ff. 103-110); XV: 8 (ff. 111-118); XVI: 8 (ff. 119-126); XVII: 8 (127-134); XVIII: 4 (ff. 135-138).</p>
<p>Catchwords in centre of lower margin of last leaf of almost every quire. No quire signatures.</p>
</collation>
<layout columns="2" writtenLines="30"><p>Ruled in pale red ink, 2 colums, 30 lines.</p></layout>
<msWriting hands="1">
<handDesc><p>1 scribe; Gothic book hand in 2 sizes according to the liturgical function. 
</p><p>F. 1 is blank (later ex-libris on recto; probationes pennae on verso).</p> 
</handDesc></msWriting> 
 
    <decoration>
      <decoNote><p>Finely executed initials and borders consisting of one
	  illuminated historiated 6 line initial with a painted border,
	  described separately; two illuminated 4 line initials with gilt
	  floral decoration and a painted half border with flowers and leaves,
	  f. <locus>46r</locus>, <locus>124v</locus>; six illuminated 3 line
	  initials with floral decoration f. <locus>88r</locus>,
	  <locus>97r</locus>, <locus>103r</locus>, <locus>108r</locus>,
	  <locus>116v</locus>, <locus>131v</locus>. Also hundreds of gilt champ
	  initials against a background in blue and mauve decorated with fine
	  white lines divided in three sizes: 3 lines in height; 2 lines,
	  including KL monograms in the calendar f. 2r - 7v; 1 line initials,
	  and line fillers of similar design on f. 13r - 13v.</p> 
	<p>Detailed description: f. <locus>8r</locus>: Illuminated historiated
	  initial E in blue with oxydized floral decoration in silver on the
	  body of the letter, inscribed in a gilt square compartment with a
	  frame in black ink. The centre of the initial is occupied by a
	  monochrome gilt representation of a standing figure in a mantle and a
	  topped hat, facing right and holding a scroll between two
	  perpendicular bars against a pinkish purple background with darker
	  tones for shadows. The floriated border covers the entire left margin
	  and half the upper and lower margins, leaving the right text column
	  unaccentuated. The border is filled with acantus leaves in blue and
	  gold, violets in violet, pink and blue, flower buds in gold, leaves
	  in light green and small spermazoid space fillers in black ink. The
	  border is framed by at thin red line complemented by a gilt line to
	  the right.</p>  
	<p>Style: The characteristic technique with minute strokes in gilt
	  against a monochrome background is totally coherent with the high
	  quality illuminations of Tours from the second half of the 15th
	  century associated with the workshop of <name>Jean
	    Fouquet</name>. Close affinities are found in a Psalter with
	  Swedish provenance, dated to c. 1450 (Gyllene böcker, nyförvärv och
	  nyupptäckter, Stockholm 1987, Cat. Nr. 60 Stockholm, Riksarkivet
	  Nynäs: manuskript nr 1). The composition of the border also suggests
	  a date in the third quarter of the 15th century.</p> 
	<p>Iconography: The identity of the standing figure on
	  f. <locus>8r</locus> as a prophet is suggested by the scroll and the
	  oriental hat. The text <q>Ecce dies veniunt dicit dominus et
	    suscitabo David</q> Ier. 23:5 identifies him as
	  <name>Jeremiah</name>.</p>
      </decoNote> 
    </decoration>

    <bindingDesc>
      <binding><p>Gold-tooled green straight grain leather binding. Sweden,
	  Lund, unsigned but Lars Magnus Berggren  after 1840. (cfr. Karlson
	  1939, pp. 248-49; Rudbeck vol. 3, 1914 pp. 40-41). Size: 186 x 135 x
	  30 mm.</p> 
	<p>Green artificial straight grain leather binding over
	  pasteboards. Backed and rounded spine. Hollow back. Gilt title and
	  white paper library label at the upper part of the back. Endbands of
	  green leather. Gilt edges. Plain single flyleaves, made endleaves and
	  doublures of dark purple moiré paper and with gilt frames. Green
	  leather hinges. All along sewing on five recessed cords. The inner
	  joint of the lower cover cracked and the bookblock in part detached
	  from the board. </p> 
	<p>The covers are tooled with a fat blind border fillet, an inner gilt
	  double lined fillet enclose a large centrepiece of undulating rococo
	  ornaments together with naturalistic birds, butterflies and flowers
	  in a neo-rococo style. The back is gilt with rococo ornaments to a
	  central ogival panel containing the title. Edges and turn-ins are
	  gilt with a single fillet.</p>
      </binding> 
    </bindingDesc>


<foliation><p>Modern foliation in pencil in upper right corner of recto.</p></foliation>

<additions><p>Various added notes in the calendar in several hands; addenda on ff. 94r and 98r; a pointing hand on f. 110v.</p></additions>
  </physDesc>
<history>
<origin><p>France, Tours, later half of 15th century. The ex-libris on f. 1r: <q>Breviarium ad usum monasterii S. Juliani Turonensis Congr. Sti Mauri</q> might indicate that the book was still in the possession of the monastery in the 17th century, cfr. the acquisition register, LUBA A IV b Nr. 10 and the correspondence with Dom R.-J. Hesbert, LUBA, Handskr. avd. korresp. Br fr/till utl.: Franskspr./ Tyskspr. 1861-1981.</p>
</origin>
<acquisition><p>According to the old catalogue card, the manuscript entered the University library in 1842 as a gift from Christian Gissel Berlin (1800-1863), professor of  Mathematics at the university, vicar of Balkåkra and member of parliament. In the acquisition register from that period however the year of entry is not mentioned. On f. i verso former library shelf mark: <q>Bibl. Mscr. H. L. a) 8o 7</q> and on front pastedown a library label with the current call number <q>Medelt.-handskr. 38</q>.</p></acquisition>
</history>
<additional>
<adminInfo>
<recordHist>
<source>Catalogued <date>Spring of 2004.</date> by Maria Sandomirskaia/Eva Nilsson Nylander.</source>
<change>
<date rend="creation">2005-09-23</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record uploaded</item>
</change>
<change>
<date rend="revision">2005-09-23</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record revised</item>
</change>
</recordHist>
<remarks rend="audience">
<p>external</p>
</remarks>
</adminInfo>
<listBibl>
<bibl>
	<editor>Hesbert, Renato-Joanne</editor>
	<title level="m">Corpus Antiphonalium Officii. V. Fontes earumque prima ordinatio. (Series Maior. Fontes. XI). </title>
	<imprint>
	  <pubPlace>Roma</pubPlace>
	  <date>1975</date>
<biblScope type="pages">p. 10</biblScope>
	</imprint>
      </bibl>
</listBibl>
</additional>
</msDescription>
