<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<msDescription id="Mh_43b">
<msIdentifier>
<country reg="SE">Sweden</country>
<settlement>Lund</settlement>
<repository key="Mh">Lund University Library</repository>
<idno>Medeltidshandskrift 43b</idno>
<altName type="database-identifier">scriptorium:Mh:538812:1127727987</altName>
</msIdentifier>
<msHeading>
    <title lang="ENG">Liturgical manual for the Roskilde diocese</title> 
    <origPlace>Denmark (Roskilde?)</origPlace>
    <origDate notBefore="1500" notAfter="1600">16th century</origDate>
    <textLang langKey="LAT">Latin</textLang>
    <note>
      <p>The manuscript is bound with, and a handwritten continuation of,
	<title type="uniform">Canon secundum usum ecclesie Rosckildensis. Cum
	  aliquibus missis et communi sanctorum optime correctus</title>
	(ff. 4r-79r), printed in Nyborg in 1522 (with shelfmark
	Paleot. Da. 1522).</p>
    </note> 
  </msHeading>
<physDesc>
    <support><p>Paper</p></support>
    <extent>ff. ii + 132 +
      i<dimensions><height>210</height><width>155</width></dimensions>mm.
    </extent> 
    <bindingDesc>
      <binding><p>Blind-tooled brown leather binding, decorated covers Denmark,
	  contemporary with the manuscript. Sweden 20th century. Size: 220 x
	  170 x 33 mm.</p> 
	<p>Brown leather binding over thin square edged wooden
	  boards. Rebinding with covers from former binding and leather
	  fragment of the back preserved on the new covering. Leather ties at
	  head, tail and fore-edge of the covers, one tie broken. Rounded
	  spine. Tight back with three double raised bands. Embroidered
	  endbands of beige linen. Former edge trimming preserved together with
	  two textmarkers at fore-edge (defect). Single plain flyleaves and
	  separate pastedowns of paper. Former pastedowns restored and
	  preserved as additional flyleaves. All along sewing on three double
	  cords laced through the boards.</p> 
	<p>The covers are blind-tooled with two frames made of triple fillets
	  and repeated tools. The outer frame contains a repeated
	  lozenge-shaped burning heart and the inner frame a lozenge-shaped
	  flower, the corner compartments a circular Christ motif. The central
	  panel is stamped with a repeated apocalyptic Madonna (cfr. Schunke
	  1979 p. 199 nr. 51) and a flower.</p></binding> 
    </bindingDesc>
  </physDesc>
<additional>
<adminInfo>
<recordHist>
<source/>
<change>
<date rend="creation">2005-09-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record uploaded</item>
</change>
<change>
<date rend="revision">2005-09-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record revised</item>
</change>
</recordHist>
</adminInfo>
</additional>
</msDescription>
