<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<msDescription id="Mh_48">
<msIdentifier>
<country reg="SE">Sweden</country>
<settlement>Lund</settlement>
<institution>Lund Observatory</institution>
<repository key="Mh">Lund University Library</repository>
<idno>Medeltidshandskrift 48</idno>
<altName type="former shelfmark">Astron.</altName>
<altName type="database-identifier">scriptorium:Mh:194492:1127733593</altName>
</msIdentifier>
<msHeading>
    <title lang="ENG">Miscellany: Astronomy</title> 
    <origPlace>Italy (?)</origPlace>
    <origDate notBefore="1444.01.01" notAfter="1444.12.31">15th century (1444)</origDate>
    <textLang langKey="LAT">Latin</textLang>
    <note><p>The manuscript contains among other things texts by Johannes de
	Sacrobosco, <title type="uniform">De sphaera</title> and <title type="uniform">Computus</title>.</p> 
      <p>In deposition.</p></note>
  </msHeading>
<physDesc>
    <support><p>Paper</p></support>
    <extent>ff. i + 97 +
      i<dimensions><height>210</height><width>150</width></dimensions>mm.
    </extent> 

    <decoration>
      <decoNote><p>Astronomical diagrams in red and brown ink, either occupying
	  between a third and full page on ff. <locus>3v</locus>,
	  <locus>16r</locus>, <locus>17r</locus>, <locus>60r</locus>,
	  <locus>96v</locus>, <locus>97r</locus>, <locus>97v</locus>, described
	  separately below, or smaller diagrams in red ink occupying lower
	  margins or smaller part of the written space, on
	  f. <locus>48v</locus>, <locus>49r</locus>, <locus>50r</locus>,
	  <locus>51r</locus>, <locus>52r</locus>.</p> 
	<p>Space left for circular diagrams on ff. 23v, 26r, 31v, 33r, 35v,
	  45r.</p> 
	<p>One decorated initial on f. <locus>60v</locus>; Small perspective
	  drawing of a dice in brown and red, with four partly erased
	  preparatory sketches, in lower and left margins on
	  f. <locus>94v</locus>.</p> 
	<p>Detailed description:
	  <list>
	    <item>f. <locus>3v</locus>: Diagram occupying the
	      lower right third of the page, depicting the spheres of the
	      elements, the moon, the sun and the planets and stars surrounding
	      the earth with its poles;</item>
	    <item>f. <locus>16r</locus>: Large circular diagram with Sol on
	      top, in red ink with the drawing of a face in brown, Terra in the
	      centre and Cauda draconis at the bottom, vertically placed within
	      a system of orbital circles, illustrating a moon eclipse
	      (?);</item>
	    <item>f. <locus>17r</locus>: Unfinished diagram with two
	      circles;</item> 
	    <item>f. <locus>60r</locus>: Large diagram in brown ink with
	      circles and the four cardinal points;</item>
	    <item>f. <locus>60v</locus>: Three line initial D in red, with
	      geometric filling and leaf decoration with graphite extending in
	      upper margin;</item>
	    <item>f. <locus>96v</locus>: Unfinished circular diagram in brown
	      ink;</item>
	    <item>f. <locus>97r</locus>: Diagram in brown ink with circles,
	      illustrating the relations between Mercurius and Sol;</item>
	    <item>f. <locus>97v</locus>: Diagram in brown ink, with circles,
	      illustrating orbits of planets, but lacking explanatory
	      texts.</item> 
	  </list>
	</p> 

	<p>Style: The diagrams, probably executed by the scribe Paulus zighanus
	  in 1444, do not produce  any significant stylistic features leading
	  to the geographical origin of the manuscript. The decorated initial
	  on f. <locus>60v</locus>, however, shows typically Italian leaf
	  forms. The secondary note on f. <locus>88v</locus>, which indicates a
	  provenance at some date at Genova, together with the watermark,
	  suggests a north Italian origin.</p> 
      </decoNote>
    </decoration>

    <bindingDesc>
      <binding><p>Parchment case with turned fore-edge, sewing and endbands
	  contemporary with the manuscript. Sweden 20th century, before 1936. Size: 222 x 158 x 25 mm.</p> 
	<p>Parchment case over millboards with turned fore-edge. Bookblock partly
	  loose in case. Flat spine. Endbands of embroidered linen on white
	  leather thong. Trimmed edges. All along sewing on two white leather
	  thongs. Quire centrefolds with parchment guards. Thongs and endbands
	  later cut flush with the spine. The bookblock is hold to the case by
	  a single thread sewn through first and last quire and the pastedown
	  of the case (20th century). Plain single endpaper wrapped around the
	  bookblock and glued to the spine. The parchment case has plain paper
	  pastedowns.</p></binding> 
    </bindingDesc>
  </physDesc>
<additional>
<adminInfo>
<recordHist>
<change>
<date rend="creation">2005-09-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record uploaded</item>
</change>
<change>
<date rend="revision">2005-09-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record revised</item>
</change>
</recordHist>
</adminInfo>
<listBibl>
      <bibl>
	<author>Hedlund, M.</author>
	<title level="m">Die Handschriften Schwedens ausgenommen UB Uppsala,
	  unter Leitung von Jan-Olof Tjäder, herausgegeben von Monica
	  Hedlund. 1. Text. 2. Tafeln</title> 
	<title level="s">Katalog der datierten Handschriften in lateinischen
	  Schrift vor 1600 in Schweden</title> 
	<biblScope type="volume">II:1-2</biblScope> 
	<imprint>
	  <pubPlace>Stockholm</pubPlace>
	  <date>1980</date>
	</imprint>
	<biblScope type="pages">p. 23</biblScope>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
</additional>
</msDescription>
