<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<msDescription id="Mh_53">
<msIdentifier>
<country reg="SE">Sweden</country>
<settlement>Lund</settlement>
<repository key="Mh">Lund University Library</repository>
<idno>Medeltidshandskrift 53</idno>
<altName type="former shelfmark">Teol.</altName>
<altName type="database-identifier">scriptorium:Mh:579771:1127737297</altName>
</msIdentifier>
<msHeading>
    <title lang="ENG">Miscellany: Theology </title> 
    <origPlace>France (?)</origPlace>
    <origDate notBefore="1400" notAfter="1500">15th century</origDate>
    <textLang langKey="FRE">French, with Picardic influence</textLang>
    <note><p>The manuscript contains interpretative treatises in prose and
	poetry on various religious subjects.</p></note> 
  </msHeading>
<physDesc>
    <support><p>Parchment</p></support>
    <extent>ff. i + 138 +
      i,<dimensions><height>155</height><width>105-110</width></dimensions>mm.
    </extent>

    <decoration>
      <decoNote><p>The decoration consists of four delicately pen flourished
	  initials and a few line fillers in blue and red on
	  f. <locus>1r</locus>, <locus>4r</locus>, <locus>6r</locus>,
	  <locus>60r</locus>, <locus>61v</locus>, <locus>62r</locus>.</p> 

	<p>Detailed description:

	  <list>
	    <item>f. <locus>1r</locus>: Intarsiated initial N,
	      three lines in height,  in blue and red with minutely
	      filigranated filling in blue and fluently waving pen flourishes
	      in blue, except for when bordering to the intarsiated blue areas
	      of the letter where the pen flourishes are red, extending into
	      upper margin and along all of left margin;</item>

	    <item>f. <locus>41r</locus>: Initial P, three lines in height, in
	      blue with filligranated filling and surrounding pen flourishes in
	      red. Initial T, three lines in height,  in red with filigranated
	      filling and pen flourishes in blue extending along left
	      margin;</item> 

	    <item>f. <locus>82r</locus>: Intarsiated initial N, five lines in
	      height, in red and green with minutely executed filigranated
	      filling in blue, and surronded by filigranated pen flourishes in
	      blue, except for red when bordering to the green intarsiated
	      fields. Badly worn.
	    </item>
	  </list>
	</p>

      </decoNote> 
    </decoration>

    <bindingDesc>
      <binding><p>Gold-tooled red morocco binding, late 18th or early 19th
	  century. Size: 160 x 120 x 30 mm.</p> 
	<p>Red morocco binding over millboards. Rounded and backed
	  spine. Hollow back with five false bands. Embroidered green, red and
	  white silk endbands. Edges gilt. Made endpapers and pastedowns of
	  comb marbled paper, front flyleaf loose. The joint of the upper board
	  is cracked and the bookblock detached from the cover. All along
	  sewing on five cords.</p> 
	<p>The covers are gilt with a border and panel of double and triple
	  line fillets; arabesques stamps in each outer corner of the inner
	  panel. Gilt library stamp in lower cover panel. The back is divided
	  into six gilt double line fillet panels with centre and corner
	  arabesques stamps. The turn-ins are gilt with two ornamental rolls in
	  renaissance style.</p>
      </binding> 
    </bindingDesc>
  </physDesc>
<additional>
<adminInfo>
<recordHist>
<source/>
<change>
<date rend="creation">2005-09-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record uploaded</item>
</change>
<change>
<date rend="revision">2005-09-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record revised</item>
</change>
</recordHist>
</adminInfo>
</additional>
</msDescription>
