<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<msDescription id="Mh_57">
  <msIdentifier>
    <country reg="SE">Sweden</country>
    <settlement>Lund</settlement>
    <repository key="Mh">Lund University Library</repository>
    <idno>Medeltidshandskrift 57</idno>
    <altName lang="SWE" type="former shelfmark">Kyrkohist.</altName>
    <altName type="database-identifier">scriptorium:Mh:321519:1146049063</altName>
  </msIdentifier>
  <msHeading>
    <title lang="ENG">Synaxarion, September - February</title> 
    <origPlace>Constantinople</origPlace>
    <origDate notBefore="1350" notAfter="1370">14th century, mid (c. 1360)</origDate>
    <textLang langKey="GRK">Greek</textLang>
    <note><p>The manuscript belongs to the family
    M* of H. Delehaye's survey, cols. XXXVIII - XLVI. The brevity of Delehaye's
    manuscript descriptions makes it difficult to establish the place of
    Medeltidshandskrift 57 within the M*-group, but it seems reasonable to
    suppose a close affinity between Mh 57 and the manuscript Ma (Codex
    bibliothecae Caesaraeae Petropolitanae gr. 231).</p></note>
  </msHeading>
  <msContents>

   <msItem n="1">
     <locus from="1r" to="50v">ff. 1r-50v</locus>
     <title type="uniform">September</title>

     <rubric lang="GRK">ΒΙΒΛΊΟΝ ΣΥΝΑΞΆΡΙΟΝ τῆς συνόψεως τῶν
     ἁγί(ων) τοῦ ὅλου χρόνου, ὅθεν τὲ ἕκαστος καὶ ἐκ τίνων ἔφυ καὶ ἐν οἷς
     χρόνοις, καὶ εἴτε τὸν διὰ μαρτυρίου εἴτε τὸν δι᾿ ἀσκήσεως ἐδέξατο
     στέφανον</rubric>

     <incipit lang="GRK">Μὴν σεπτέμβριος ἔχων ἡμέρας λʹ. ἡ
     ἡμέρα ἔχει ὥρας ιβʹ καὶ ἡ νὺξ ὥρας δώδεκα. ἰστέον ὅτι τὴν ἰνδικτιῶνα
     ἑορτάζει ἡ τοῦ Θ(εο)ῦ ἐκκλησία ἀπὸ τῶν ἀρχαίων παραλαβοῦσα διὰ τὸ
     νομίζεσθαι παρὰ Ῥωμαίοις ἀρχὴν εἶναι ἔτους ἀπὸ ταύτης τῆς
     ἰνδικτιῶνος. ἰνδικτιὼν γὰρ λέγεται παρὰ Ῥωμαίοις ὁ ὁρισμός. καὶ πρόσετι,
     διὰ τὸ κατ᾿ αὐτὴν τὴν ἡμέραν εἰσελθεῖν τὸν Κ(ύριο)ν ἡμῖν εἰς τὴν
     συναγωγὴν τ(ῶν) Ἰουδαίων</incipit>
   </msItem>

   <msItem n="2">
     <locus from="51r" to="120r">ff. 51r-120r</locus> <title
     type="uniform">October</title> <incipit
     lang="GRK">Μὴν ὀκτώβριος ἔχων ἡμέρας λαʹ. ἡ ἡμέρα ἔχει ὥρας ιαʹ κ(αὶ) ἡ
     νὺξ ὥρας ιγʹ. ἐν τῆ πρώτη· μνήμη τοῦ ἁγίου ἀπο(στόλου) Ἀνανίου</incipit>
   </msItem>

   <msItem n="3">
     <locus from="120r" to="172v">ff. 120r-172v</locus> <title
     type="uniform">November</title> <incipit
     lang="GRK">Μὴν νοέμβριος ἔχων ἡμέρας λʹ. ἡ ἡμέρα ἔχει ὥρας ιʹ καὶ ἡ νὺξ
     ὥ(ρας) ιδʹ. εἰς τὴν πρώτην· τῶν ἁγίων κ(αὶ) θαυματουργῶν ἀναργύ(ρων)
     Κοσμᾶ καὶ Δαμιανοῦ</incipit>
   </msItem>

   <msItem n="4">
     <locus from="172v" to="223r">ff. 172v-223r</locus> <title
     type="uniform">December</title> <incipit
     lang="GRK">Μὴν δεκέμβριος ἔχων ἡμέρας λαʹ. ἡ ἡμέρα ἔχει ὥρας θʹ καὶ ἡ νὺξ
     ὥρας ιεʹ. εἰς τὴν πρώτην· μνήμη τοῦ ἁγίου προφήτου Ναούμ</incipit>
   </msItem>

   <msItem n="5">
     <locus from="223r" to="263v">ff. 223r-263v</locus>
     <title type="uniform">January</title>

     <incipit lang="GRK">Μὴν ἰαννουάριος ἔχων ἡμέρας λαʹ. ἡ
     ἡμέρα ἔχει ὥρ(ας) ιʹ καὶ ἡ νὺξ ὥρας ιδʹ. εἰς τὴν αην· ἡ κατὰ σάρκα
     περιτομὴ τοῦ Κ(υρίο)υ καὶ Θ(εο)ῦ καὶ Σ(ωτῆρο)ς ἡμ(ῶν) Ἰ(ησο)ῦ
     Χ(ριστο)ῦ</incipit>
   </msItem>

   <msItem n="6">
     <locus from="263v" to="297v">ff. 263v-297v</locus> <title
     type="uniform">February</title> <incipit
     lang="GRK">Μὴν φεβρουάριος ἔχει ἡμέρας κηʹ. ἡ ἡμέρα ἔχει ὥρας ιβʹ καὶ ἡ
     νῢξ ὥ(ρας) ιγʹ. εἰς τὴν αην· μνήμη τοῦ ἁγίου μ(άρτυ)ρος
     Τρύφωνος</incipit>

     <explicit lang="GRK">πολλὰς θαυμάτων ἐνεργείας
     ἐνδειξάμενος κ(αὶ) οὕτω πρὸς Κ(ύριο)ν ἐξεδήμησεν :– τῆ αὐτῆ ἡμέρα,
     μνή(μη) τοῦ ὁσίου</explicit>

   </msItem>
 </msContents>
 <physDesc>
   <support><p>Paper (parchment leaf
   A).</p><watermarks><p>Four different
   watermarks: 1) Most frequent is a pomegranate on a stem with two pairs of
   leaves, occurring in quires no. 1-11 and 22-27. One might compare with the
   fairly similar Fruit: Grenade 4187 from the year 1363 in V. A. Mošin et
   S. M. Traljić, Filigranes des XIIIe et XIVe ss., I-II, Zagreb
   1957. According to Mošin and Traljić this type of watermark appeared in
   Italy around 1360. 2) In quires no. 11-21 we find a letter-combination in
   the form of two 'G's one above the other, bisected by a line and with a
   patriarchal cross above. Cf. Mošin and Traljić Lettres 5738 (1375/85), and
   Briquet lettres assembles 9415 (1354) of Italian provenance. Almost
   identical but with just one crossbar: Keinz 40, undated (F. Keinz, Die
   Wasserzeichen des XIV. Jahrhunderts in Handschriften der k. bayer. Hof- und
   Staatsbibliothek, Abh. d. I. Cl. d. k. Ak. d. Wiss. XX. Bd. III. Abth.,
   München 1894-1897). 3) The Bow-and-arrow occurring in quires no. 27-38 is
   remotely similar to Mošin and Traljić Arc 368 (1370); see also Bogen und
   Pfeil X 1680 (Perugia 1361) in G. Piccard, Wasserzeichen Werkzeug und
   Waffen (Findbuch IX), Stuttgart 1980, and Bow-and-arrow 3786 (1372) in
   Likhachev's Watermarks, I-II, (=Monumenta chartae papyraceae historiam
   illustrantia, XV) ed. J. S. G. Simmons and B. J. van Ginneken-van de
   Kasteele, Amsterdam 1994 (Russian original St Petersburg 1899). 4) Two
   keys, addorsed, single-line, with a line (or possibly a cross now lacking
   the cross bar - cf. Briquet, vol. I p. 241: "La croix fait assez souvent
   défaut") above. Similar is Briquet deux clefs 3815 (1362). This watermark
   appears only once in the ms, on f. 270 (quire
   no. 35).</p></watermarks></support><extent>ff. i + A + 297 +
   i,<dimensions><height>295</height><width
  >215</width></dimensions>mm.</extent>

   <collation><p>38 quires: I: 7 (ff. 1-7, one
   leaf has been cut out after f. 5 with resulting loss of text); II:
   (ff. 8-15); III: 8 (ff. 16-23); IV: 8 (ff. 24-31); V: 8 (ff. 32-39); VI: 8
   (ff. 40-47); VII: 8 (ff. 48-55); VIII: 8 (ff. 56-63); IX: 8 (ff. 64-71); X:
   8 (ff. 72-79); XI: 8 (ff. 80-87); XII: 8 (ff. 88-95); XIII: 8 (ff. 96-103);
   XIV: 7 (ff. 104-110, there is a guard from a cut out leaf after f. 109, but
   the text is intact); XV: 7 (ff. 111-117, one torn out leaf after f. 116
   with resulting loss of text); XVI: 8 (ff. 118-125); XVII: 8 (ff. 126-133);
   XVIII: 8 (ff. 134-141); XIX: 4 (ff. 142-145, after f. 143 there are 4
   leaves missing with resulting loss of text); XX: 8 (ff. 146-153); XXI: 8
   (ff. 154-161); XXII: 8 (ff. 162-169); XXIII: 8 (ff. 170-177); XXIV: 8
   (ff. 178-185); XXV: 8 (ff. 186-193); XXVI: 8 (ff. 194-201); XXVII: 8
   (ff. 202-209); XXVIII: 8 (ff. 210-217); XXIX: 8 (ff. 218-225); XXX: 8
   (ff. 226-233); XXXI: 8 (ff. 234-241); XXXII: 8 (ff. 242-249); XXXIII: 8
   (ff. 250-257); XXXIV: 8 (ff. 258-265); XXXV: 8 (ff. 266-273); XXXVI: 8
   (ff. 274-281); XXXVII: 8 (ff. 282-289); XXXVIII: 8 (ff. 290-297). Beside
   the modern flyleaves there is one parchment leaf ('A') preceding the actual
   synaxarion. The parchment is now very dark and wrinkled but seems to have
   been of good quality originally. Probably 12th century. Writing area
   205/210 x 145 mm. Ruling type Sautel 22D1 (or possibly 22C1, it is
   difficult to see, due to cutting of the inner margin). Dark brown ink,
   mixed minuscule script pendent from ruled lines. The text comes from
   another synaxarion and gives part of the text for May 9 and 10, mentioning
   the saints <name lang="GRK">Χρηστοφόρος</name>, <name
   lang="GRK">Ἐπίμαχος καὶ Γορδιανός</name>, <name
   lang="GRK">Κόδρας</name>, <name
   lang="GRK">Τρυφαίνη</name>, <name lang="GRK">Τιμόθεος ὁ
   πατριάρχης</name>, <name lang="GRK">Σίμων ὁ ζηλωτής</name>,
   <name lang="GRK">Ἀλφιός</name>, <name
   lang="GRK">Φιλάδελφος καὶ Κυρῖνος</name>. The wording of the narrative on
   Kodras suggests that the fragment could be related to the ms D (Codex
   bibliothecae Nationalis Parisiensis 1587) of H. Delehaye's study in
   Synaxarium Ecclesiae Constantinopolitanae, Bruxelles 1902 (Acta Sanctorum,
   Propylaeum ad Acta SS. Novembris). The ms is mutilated at the end, giving
   just two entries on the 27th of February and none for the 28th. Quire
   numbering is made in Greek numerals in two sets successively: quires 1-21
   and 22-38. The signatures are generally written (by the main scribes, it
   seems, or at least in the same ink as the rest of the text) in the lower
   righthand corners of first recto and last verso for quires no. 2 - 21, in
   the middle of or the outer corners of lower margin for quires no. 22 -
   37. Some signatures are missing altogether, a few of them probably trimmed
   away or lost due to ripping of the page. Although originally made up of
   quaterniones the bookblock is now bound together in much larger units. To
   prevent the well used book from falling apart one has at rebinding taken
   some 18-20 leaves at a time, overcasting them tightly at the spine. Thus
   the binding threads which are visible inside these units cannot be taken as
   proof of an irregular quire organisation, and accordingly the old quire
   signatures are still valid.</p></collation>

   <layout columns="2" writtenLines="30-33"><p
  >Blind ruling; written space on ff. 1-161: 205 x 145 mm. text
   in 2 columns with 3o lines at 65 mm. with an intercolumnium of 13
   mm.</p></layout>

   <msWriting hands="2">
     <handDesc>
       <p>The manuscript was copied by two contemporary
       scribes, scribe A wrote ff. 1-161, scribe B ff. 162-297. Only on
       f. 191v a third hand seems to appear. None of them are as yet
       identified. No subscription is preserved, since the final leaves are
       lost. The script of the first part of the manuscript is clear and
       regular, slightly inclined to the left. A prominent feature of the
       script is the forceful pen strokes at the base of the letters <q
       lang="GRK">ξ</q> and <q lang="GRK">ζ</q>
       ending in a NW-SE-diagonal, which is also taken up by <q
       lang="GRK">χ</q>, <q lang="GRK">λ</q>, and <q
       lang="GRK">δ.</q> Note also the shorthand <q
       lang="GRK">και</q> linked to next letter, further the
       rather conspicuous - <q lang="GRK">ος</q> ligatures as
       in <q lang="GRK">πρò</q> at the end of lines
       (cf. f. 102r). Though coming from a skilled hand the style gives rather
       an uncouth impression. Blackish-brown and mild orange-red ink in good
       preservation.</p>

     <p>The second part of the manuscript (ff. 162-297) shows
     more of a scholar's hand. It is upright or very slightly inclined to the
     right. Brown and light red ink, the latter in a strongly faded
     condition. The large thetas and omegas dominate the script together with
     other overdimensioned circular forms in e.g.<q
     lang="GRK">α, ο,</q> and <q lang="GRK">φ</q>
     ('Fettaugenmode'). At the end of lines the punctuation marks are
     sometimes inscribed within the spacious C-sigma, omicron or
     upsilon.</p></handDesc>
   </msWriting> 

   <decoration>
     <decoNote><p>Head pieces, tituli and most
     of the other decorative elements are in faded red ink - some linefillers
     and elaborate initials combine black and red ink. The headpieces for
     September, October, and November, height 30-40 mm, are in Laubsägestil;
     the rectangular frame contains a billowy arabesque with halfpalmettes and
     knobs, lily- or palmette shaped corner decorations, and, in the middle of
     the top border, a threefold loop or Dreierschlinge (fully worked out in
     the September piece, only suggested in the following two). The red ink is
     used for contouring but also for filling up the background
     (Aussparungstechnik). The headpieces for the following three months show
     a Flechtband-construction in the form of a ribbon interlacedly crossing
     itself while passing through ribbon ovals. The ends of the ribbon are
     shaped as lilies.  At the end of each day in the synaxarion we find a
     delimiting linefiller, the design of which in the first half of the book
     (=scribe A) varies considerably, while in the second half scribe B has
     kept to a more restricted set of rather simple geometrical/vegetal
     ornaments. This contrast between the two scribes is reflected also in the
     design of the initials.  Elaborate red (occasionally red and black)
     initials project into the margin and in the space between the two columns
     at the outset of all narratives. On ff. 1-161 the oblong initials, 20-45
     mm. in size, show two basic structures: the unfilled Laubsäge/Palmetten
     type and the filled silhouette/bead-and-reel type with additional
     embellishments of beads and strokes. There are some examples of
     zoomorphic initials and linefillers, chiefly single or double snakes
     (ff. <locus>19r</locus>, <locus
    >29v</locus>, <locus>34v</locus>, <locus
    >61v</locus>, <locus>68v</locus>, <locus
    >108v</locus>, <locus>112v</locus>, <locus
    >120v</locus>, <locus>142v</locus>, <locus
    >159v</locus>). Two fish-initials (omicron), on f. <locus
    >78r</locus> and f. <locus>89v</locus> .
     &gt;From f. 162 onwards the initials are quite plain and of lesser
     dimensions (height 10-20mm). The elaboration is often just a couple of
     swellings and a small beaded tendril at the base. Rubrication is also
     used for the commemoration of each saint, i.e. for the opening remark
     which sometimes stands alone but mostly precedes the ensuing verse(s) and
     the narrative of the saint. Furthermore, all iambic or hexametral lines
     are indicated by small majuscule or minuscule initials in
     red.</p></decoNote>
   </decoration>

   <bindingDesc>
     <binding><p>Blind-tooled dark brown
     goatskin binding, preserved covers of Byzantine binding; Greece,
     contemporary with the manuscript. Rebinding, 20th century. Size: 310 x
     225 x 95 mm.</p>

     <p>Dark brown goatskin binding over thick, grooved, square
     edged wooden boards with rounded inner face at the spine (type a and k,
     cfr. Szirmai 1999, p. 75; type 19.5 and 20.3, cfr. Frederici and Houlis
     1988 p. 28). Rebinding with upper cover and back of black calfskin and
     with lower cover from former binding. Dark brown covering material of
     upper board and back from former binding preserved, but partly missing on
     the new covering. Small white paper label with the number 793 at the
     centre of the upper cover. Two fastenings at fore-edge missing (holes at
     lower cover fore-edge type 32.4, cfr. Frederici and Houlis 1988,
     p. 39). Rounded spine with lining of blue grey cloth. Tight
     back. Blind-tooled white library cloth label at the top of the
     back. Natural coloured primary endbands embroidered on double supports
     extending over the boards. The endbands are attached by the sewing thread
     by several holes on the inner face of each board (fig. 6.10, cfr. Szirmai
     1999, p. 77; fig. 26.3, cfr. Frederici and Houlis 1988, p. 35). The
     endbands are restored and partly damaged. Former edge trimming
     preserved. No squares. One plain paper flyleaf, 20th century, mounted on
     the first and last manuscript page of the bookblock. Upper board with a
     half paper pastedown; on the inside of the upper board in black ink: <q
     lang="GRK">Cυναξάριν ςʹ μην(ων) | σεπτεμβ(ριος) ε(ως)
     φεβ(ρουαριου)</q> and on the inside of the lower board, rather coarsely:
     <q lang="GRK">πε μα ‚αφ ασπρ(ων) | ͵ςσο ασπρ(ων) | χρεω |
     τό λγθετϊ.</q> The original (most likely link-stitch) sewing on three
     sewing stations is repaired by assembling and oversewing leaves into
     thick gatherings of 18 to 20 leaves each. The original sewing thread is
     broken at joints but remains in holes of the boards and in centrefolds of
     the gatherings.  The covers are blind-tooled to a frame of double fillets
     containing two rows of a repeated rectangular stamp with heart-shaped
     forms (cfr. Vat. gr. 1297, cfr. Frederici and Houlis 1988, p. 56). The
     central panel is divided into four compartments each divided by fillets
     into a saltire. (fig. 37.6, cfr. Federici and Houlis 1988, p. 66). The
     fillets of the compartments are stamped with a small four-petal flower
     and the concurrences of the fillets with a tool of concentric
     circles. The compartments of the lower cover are decorated with a
     symmetric trapeze-shaped tool showing a lily on a blind bottom and the
     upper cover compartments with a circular tool possibly of a two-headed
     eagle. The back is blind-tooled with a double fillet to a fishbone
     pattern with concentric circles at the top of each superposed and
     inversed V-form.</p></binding>
   </bindingDesc>


   <foliation><p>Foliated in pencil by modern
   cataloguer in upper right corner.</p>
   </foliation>

   <additions><p>Marginal entries: f. <locus
  >1r</locus>, by scribe A, upper margin: <q
   lang="GRK">ἡγοῦ ἰ(ησοῦ) τῶν ἐμῶν πονημάτ(ων)</q>, and lower margin: <q
   lang="GRK">στί(χοι) τῆ ἰνδ(ίκτω)· ἴνδικτον ἡμῖν εὐλόγει νέου
   χρόνου, ὦ κ(αὶ) παλαιὲ καὶ δι᾿ ἀν(θρώπ)ους νέε</q>, i.e. the iambic
   distichon for the first day. On f. <locus>3r</locus>, lower
   margin, and f. <locus>4v</locus>, upper margin, two notes in
   black ink (15th - 16th century?): <q lang="GRK"> εἰσ τών
   γραμ(ματι)κόν · ηγιέσ πωλέσ καὶ χερετήσμ(ατα) ἀπὸ των μάρκον δεομ(αι) των
   θ(εό)ν · του | εὐρῆν σέ η γραφή μου · εν ἡγι(ει)α καὶ χαρήν · καὶ ἡμεῖσ
   μ(ετα) το ελεόσ τοῦ θ(εο)ῦ. ζωμεν τοῦ | ?θ(είου) μαρκο · δχτ · κ`ο · γγ´´ ·
   αθανυ ´ · πεο · γγ´´ μπαρτζη · ?εγρεσ · μπηγ · αλη μπηγ · μουσταφᾶ and πολα
   προσκυνήματα · κ(αὶ) χαιρετήσματα απώ αἱμενα τω μάρκοσ · ησ την π(α)π(α)
   γεργϊσ μπώρισ | να μή βλεπῆσ τω σπϊτι μοῦ · δεν τω παρῆσ · τω κράσϊ : κ(αὶ)
   τω σϊταρϊ κ(αὶ) τω λαθῦρϊ · κ(αὶ) τω | βρομῆ κ(αὶ) ωλο το σπιτϊ · εσ
   εξεβρῆσ :– ωτϊ εγω ξαιρο · ωλα :–. On f. <locus>50v</locus>,
   in monokondylic style, by the main scribe: τελος σεπτεμβριου μηνος, and, in
   a different hand and ink, a prayer formula in Church slavonic. On f. <locus
  >181r</locus>: ετοc ζρλθ μηνὶ δηκέβρηοc ειc ζʹ ημερα τετραδη
   | εχη ὀνησεν ο θεοc ?στάχτη</q>, i.e. giving the date Dec. 7. 1630. On
   f. <locus>274v</locus>, upper margin, black ink: <q
   lang="GRK">ευλόγη υ ψυχὴ μοῦ τὸν κ(ύριο)ν κ(ύρι)ε ο θ(εὸ)σ
   μοῦ εμεγαλη</q> (Septuag. Ps. 103). Further notes, formulas, and pentrials,
   from different times and in different hands (not always legible), are to be
   found on f. <locus>6r</locus>; f. <locus
  >38v</locus>; f. <locus>44r</locus>; f. <locus
  >49v</locus> and <locus>50r</locus> (a 19th
   century hand?); f. <locus>51r</locus> (by the main scribe);
   f. <locus>83r</locus> and <locus>87r</locus>
   ; f. <locus>100r</locus>; f. <locus
  >151v</locus>, <locus>152r</locus> and <locus
  >158r</locus> (same hand as on f. <locus
  >49</locus> and f. <locus>50</locus>)
   mentioning the year 1854; f. <locus>158v</locus>; f. <locus
  >171v</locus>; f. <locus>180v</locus>
   (numerals, maybe a computation of the years 1630 and 1783/4); f. <locus
  >185r</locus>; f. <locus>204r</locus>
   (including a name, <name lang="GRK">μηχαελ</name>) ;
   f. <locus>205r</locus> (two blind drawings of saints, made
   through scratching the surface with a sharp tool) ; f. <locus
  >280v</locus>; f. <locus
  >286v</locus>.</p></additions>

   <condition><p>Overall the manuscript is in
   fairly good condition. There are some traces of worm and water damage, and
   especially the red ink of the latter scribe has undergone severe fading and
   can be read only with difficulty. Wax stains and overcasting along the
   inner margin give evidence to the frequent use of the
   codex.</p></condition>
 </physDesc>

 <history>
   <origin><p>Constantinople, mid 14th
   century.</p>
   </origin>

   <provenance><p>Very little is known of the
   vicissitudes of this manuscript except that the codex was acquired on the
   Peloponnese in 1920 by professor Axel W. Persson.</p></provenance>
   <acquisition><p>It was donated to the Lund
   University Library the following year (cfr. Lunds universitets
   årsredogörelse, 1921-22, p. 42). Some of the marginal entries might give
   clues as to its previous history in Greek-speaking and possibly Slavonic
   areas.</p></acquisition>
 </history>

<additional>
  <adminInfo>
    <recordHist>
      <source>
	<p>Catalogued by Eva Nyström.</p>
      </source>
      <change>
	<date rend="creation"/>
	<respStmt>
	  <name>eva</name>
	</respStmt>
	<item>Record uploaded</item>
      </change>
      <change>
	<date rend="revision">2006-05-10</date>
	<respStmt>
	  <name>eva</name>
	</respStmt>
	<item>Record revised</item>
      </change>
    </recordHist>
    <remarks rend="audience">
      <p>external</p>
    </remarks>
  </adminInfo>
  <listBibl>
    <bibl>
      <author>Devos, P.</author>
      <title level="a">Commémoraisons de martyrs persans dans
      le synaxaire de Lund</title>
      <title level="j">Analecta Bollandiana</title>
      <biblScope type="volume">81</biblScope>
      <imprint>
	<date>1963</date>
      </imprint>
      <biblScope type="pages">pp. 143-158</biblScope>
    </bibl>

    <bibl>
      <author>Rudberg, S. Y.</author>
      <title level="a">Le synaxaire grec de Lund</title>
      <title level="j">Analecta Bollandiana</title>
      <biblScope type="volume">81</biblScope>
      <imprint>
	<date>1963</date>
      </imprint>
      <biblScope type="pages">pp. 117-141</biblScope>
    </bibl>

    <bibl>
      <author>Rudberg, S. Y.</author>
      <title level="a">Les manuscrits grecs de la Bibliothèque
      universitaire de Lund,</title>
      <title level="j">Eranos</title>
      <biblScope type="volume">67</biblScope>
      <imprint>
	<date>1969</date>
      </imprint>
      <biblScope type="pages">pp. 54-61</biblScope>
    </bibl>
  </listBibl>
</additional>
</msDescription>
