<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<msDescription id="Mh_52">
<msIdentifier>
<country reg="SE">Sweden</country>
<settlement>Lund</settlement>
<repository key="Mh">Lund University Library</repository>
<idno>Medeltidshandskrift 52</idno>
<altName type="former shelfmark" lang="SWE">Rarsaml. Teol.</altName>
<altName type="database-identifier">scriptorium:Mh:843642:1127737233</altName>
</msIdentifier>
<msHeading>
  <title lang="ENG">Book of Hours</title> 
  <origPlace>Flanders/Holland (Bruges, for the use of Utrecht)</origPlace>
  <origDate notBefore="1460" notAfter="1480">15th century, later half</origDate>
  <textLang langKey="DUT">Dutch</textLang>
 </msHeading>
<msContents>
<msItem n="1">
<locus from="1r" to="2v">ff. 1r-2v</locus>
<title type="uniform">Calendar</title>
<note>In red: Gertrudis (6. 1), Pancratius (12. 5), Lebuinus (12. 11), Gereon (10. 10), Willibrordus, bishop of Utrecht (7. 11), indicating the diocese of Utrecht.</note>
</msItem>

<msItem n="2">
<locus from="13r" to="59v">ff. 13r-59v</locus>
<title type="uniform">Hours of Our Lady</title>
<rubric>Die ghetiden onser lieuer vrouwen</rubric>
<incipit>Here du salte op doen mine lippen</incipit>
<explicit>daer ic mit allen salighen gheesten minen here ende minen god mach eweliken louen Amen.</explicit>
<note><p>The initia of the hymns are quoted in Latin.</p>
<p>Ff. 59v-60r: blank.</p></note>
</msItem>

<msItem n="3">
<locus from="61r" to="75v">ff. 61r-75v</locus>
<title type="uniform">Little Hours of Our Lady</title>
<rubric>Die corte getide uan onser vrouwen</rubric>
<incipit>Maria maecht ontfaet die gruete</incipit>
<explicit>sit benedictum in secula Amen.</explicit>
<note><p>In red: <q>Hier is groot aflaet toe tot dese twe leste punten voerscreuen</q>.</p>
<p>F. 76r: blank.</p>
</note>
</msItem>

<msItem n="4">
<locus from="77r" to="85v">ff. 77r-85v</locus>
<title type="uniform">Office of the Holy Cross</title>
<rubric>Die getiden uanden heilighen cruus</rubric>
<incipit>Domine Here du salte opdoen mijn lippen</incipit>
<explicit>ende ons arme sondaren leuen ende bliscap ewelic amen.</explicit>
</msItem>

<msItem n="5">
<locus from="86r" to="112v">ff. 86r-112v</locus>
<title type="uniform">Office of the Holy Spirit</title>
<rubric>Die getiden uanden heiligen gheest</rubric>
<incipit>Here du salte op doen mijn lippen</incipit>
<explicit>Alle ghelouighe zielen moeten rusten in vreden amen.</explicit>
<note><p>The initia of the hymns are quoted in Latin.</p></note>
</msItem>

<msItem n="6">
<locus from="112v" to="124v">ff. 112v-124v</locus>
<title type="uniform">Office of the Holy Trinity</title>
<rubric>Hier na volghen die getiden uan der heiligher drieuoudicheit</rubric>
<incipit>Here wilt op doen mine lippen</incipit>
<explicit>die du o gloriose engel altoos bescouwes in eweliker ewicheit Amen.</explicit>
</msItem>

<msItem n="7">
<locus from="125r" to="212v">ff. 125r-212v</locus>
<title type="uniform">Office of the Holy Eucharist</title>
<rubric>Die ghetiden uanden heiligen sacramente</rubric>
<incipit>Pater noster etc Onse hulpe moet sijn inden name des heren</incipit>
<explicit>Die leues ende regneres in enicheit des heiligen gheestes een god ewelike sonder eynde Amen.</explicit>
<note><p>The initia of the hymns are quoted in Latin.</p></note>
</msItem>

<msItem n="8">
<locus from="213r" to="241v">ff. 213r-241v</locus>
<title type="uniform">Office of the Holy Wisdom</title>
<rubric>Die ghetiden der ewiger wijsheit</rubric>
<incipit>Mine ziele heuet di begeret</incipit>
<explicit>Die ewige wijsheit moet benedien ende bewaren onse herten ende onse lichame amen</explicit>
<note><p>F. 242r-v: blank.</p></note>
</msItem>

<msItem n="9">
<locus from="243r" to="276v">ff. 243r-276v</locus>
<title type="uniform">Office of the Holy Cross</title>
<rubric>Die ghetiden des heiligen cruus</rubric>
<incipit>Here du salte opdoen mine lippen</incipit>
<explicit>ende minen god mach ewelike louen ende dancken Amen.</explicit>
<note><p>Cfr. ff. 77r-85v.</p>
<p>F. 277r: blank but with probationes pennae.</p></note>
</msItem>

<msItem n="10">
<locus from="278r" to="298v">ff. 278r-298v</locus>
<title type="uniform">Penitential psalms with litany and prayers</title>
<rubric>Die seuen psalmen der penitencien</rubric>
<incipit>Here in dijnre uerbolghenheit en straffe mi niet</incipit>
<explicit>die sonden uerdienen Bi onsen here ihesum christum Amen</explicit>
<note><p>The saints are the above mentioned, except Gereon</p></note>
</msItem>

<msItem n="11">
<locus from="298v" to="305r">ff. 298v-305r</locus>
<title type="uniform">Liturgical prayers in translation</title>
<rubric>Die duutsche benedijst</rubric>
<incipit>Ghebenedijt den here smaect ende besiet</incipit>
<note><p>On f. 302r: <q>Dat duutsche pater noster</q></p>
<p>On f. 302v: <q>Aue maria gracia plena</q></p>
<p>On f. 303r: <q>Credo in deum p.</q></p>
<p>On f. 303v: <q>Aue salus mundi uerbum</q></p>
<p>F. 304r: blank</p>
<p>On f. 305r: <q>Corpus et sanguis domini</q> and <q>Dat eynde veers In manus t.</q></p></note>
</msItem>


    <msItem n="12">
<locus from="305r" to="327r">ff. 305r-327r</locus>
<title type="uniform">Prayers and suffrages</title>
<rubric>Van den heilighen sacrament</rubric>
<incipit>God gruet v o alre heilichste lichaem ons heren</incipit>
<explicit>settede altoos sinen wille voor dinen wille Amen.</explicit>
<note><p>For the first prayer cfr. Aue sanctissimum corpus, Haimerl pp. 70, 75.</p>
	<p>On f. 306v: <rubric>Als men onsen here god heft oracio</rubric> and
	  <incipit>Wes ghegruet waer lichaem ons heren</incipit></p>

<p>On f. 307r: <rubric>Een goet gebet</rubric> and <incipit>O Ziele christi maec mi heilich</incipit></p>
<p>On f. 307v: <rubric>Aue salus</rubric> and <incipit>Wes ghegruet salicheit der werelt</incipit></p>
<p>On f. 307v/308r: <rubric>Als men dat sacrament ontfangen heeft</rubric> and <incipit>Danc seg ic di almachtighe god</incipit></p>
	<p>On f. 308v: <rubric>Een ghebeth</rubric> and <incipit>O Minlike
	    ihesu in dine diepe wonden</incipit></p>

	<p>On f. 309r: <rubric>Een deuoet gebet</rubric> and <incipit>O God
	    vader der ewicheit</incipit> and on f. 319v: <explicit>dat ic mijn
	    sonden beteren moet ende dijn hulpe uerdienen Amen.</explicit></p>

	<p>On f. 310v: <rubric>Ghebeth</rubric> and <incipit>O Heilighe maghet
	    maria sonderlinge beelde der godformicheit</incipit> and on
	    f. 312v: <explicit>ende die heilighe gheest in ewicheit der
	      ewicheit Amen.</explicit></p>

<p>On f. 312v: <rubric>Van onser lieuer vrouwen drie gebeden mit drie Aue maria</rubric> and <incipit>O Moghende coninghinne des ewighen rijcs</incipit></p> 
<p>On f. 313r: <incipit>O Weerde ende ghebenedide moeder maria</incipit></p>
<p>On f. 314r: <incipit>O Alre zuetste maget maria Ic bidde di</incipit></p>
<p>On f. 314v: <rubric>Van sunte katrijn</rubric> and <incipit>O Alre glorioeste ende alre heilichste mertelaerster</incipit></p>
<p>On f. 316v: <rubric>Collecta</rubric> and <incipit>God die moyses die ewe gaueste</incipit></p>
<p>On f. 317r: <rubric>Van sunte barbara</rubric> and <incipit>O Here wi bidden toon ons goedertierlic v ontfermherticheit</incipit></p>
<p>On f. 317v: <rubric>Van sunte andries ap.</rubric> and <incipit>O Heilighe apostel sunte andries</incipit></p>
<p>On f. 318r: <rubric>Van sunte cristoffel mar.</rubric> and <incipit>O Suete cristoffel du eerber martelaer</incipit>; with versicle and collect.</p>
<p>On f. 318v: <rubric>Van sunte maria magdalena</rubric> and <incipit>DIt is ghetrouwe redene weerdich</incipit>; with versicle and collect.</p>
<p>On f. 319v: <rubric>Van sunte sebastiaen</rubric> and <incipit>O Heilighe salighe ridder christi</incipit>; with versicle and collect.</p>
<p>On f. 321v: <rubric>Van sunte anthonis abt</rubric> and <incipit>Die stemme sprac uanden hemel</incipit>; with versicle and collect.</p>
<p>On f. 322r: <rubric>Van allen enghelen</rubric> and <incipit>O Alle ghi heilighe seraphinnen ende cherubinnen</incipit></p>
<p>On f. 323r: <rubric>Vanden patriarchen</rubric> and <incipit>O Ghi edele patriarchen uerblijt v</incipit></p>
<p>On f. 323v: <rubric>Van den propheten</rubric> and <incipit>O Ghi weerdighe propheten waerachtige mannen</incipit></p>
<p>On f. 324v: <rubric>Van den apostolen</rubric> and <incipit>O Edele senatoren des hemels</incipit></p>
<p>On f. 325r: <rubric>Van den martelaren</rubric> and <incipit>O Ghi onuerwinlike martelaren uerblijt v</incipit></p>
<p>On f. 325v: <rubric>Van den confessoren</rubric> and <incipit>O Ghi eersam confessoren uerblijt v</incipit></p>
<p>On f. 326r: <rubric>Een ghebet uan den magheden</rubric> and <incipit>O Gi heilighe magheden die den enghelen alre gelucste sijt</incipit></p>
<p>On f. 327r: <rubric>Van onser lieuer vrouwen</rubric> and <incipit>O Vrouwe der glorien coninghinne der bliscappen</incipit></p>
<p>F. 315v: blank.</p></note>
</msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<support><p>Parchment</p></support><extent>ff. ii + 327 + ii, <dimensions><height>145</height><width>105</width></dimensions> mm.</extent>
<collation><p>Original collation destroyed when the manuscript was rebound in the 19th century.</p></collation>
<layout columns="1" writtenLines="17"><p>One column; 17 lines; ruled in red ink, pricked in outer margin often cropped but visible in ff. 38-44; written space: 85 x 60 mm.; last leaf has been cut in the outer margin.</p>
</layout>
<msWriting hands="1">
<handDesc script="gothic book hand" medium="ink" scope="sole"><p>
Gothic book-hand. One hand. Rubricated.</p></handDesc>
</msWriting> 

    <decoration>
      <decoNote><p>Five full-page illuminations (ff. 60v, 76v, 277v, 304v, 315r
	  and offprint from two more on ff. 69r, 262r); nine illuminated and
	  historiated initials (ff. 13r, 61r, 77r, 86r, 113r, 125r, 213r, 243r,
	  278r), 43 foliated borders with either thistle, strawberries, vine,
	  violets or daisies (ff. 22v, 36r, 42v, 46r, 52v, 56v, 58v, 69r, 78v,
	  79v, 83v, 84v, 91v, 97v, 103r, 105v, 109v, 114v, 116v, 120v, 122v,
	  151r, 189v, 196v, 205r, 214r, 224r, 227v, 229v, 231v, 233v, 235v,
	  239r, 251v, 256r, 259r, 262r, 264v, 267r, 271r, 274v, 299r, 305r),
	  hundreds of decorated initials, 2-4 lines, in burnished gold on
	  raised gesso ground, with fillings and frames in blue and pinkish
	  mauve with white details, and ca. 1000 pen flourished 1-line initials
	  alternatively in blue and red or gold and blue.</p>

	<p>Detailed description:</p>
	<p>f. <locus>13r</locus>: illuminated and historiated initial (H) in burnished gold
	  with standing Madonna and the child Jesus in a landscape.
	  Foliated border with
	  blue and yellow acanthus, small green leaves, small red flowers,
	  golden stars, inhabited by a yellow and a grey bird in rigt
	  margin.</p> 

	<p>f. <locus>60v</locus>: full-page illumination of Anna selbdritt seated on a wooden
	  throne with carved gothic tracery on its back, inside a blueish grey
	  stone building with landscape back-drop seen through an open window
	  and door. Anna is seated frontally holding an open book, dressed in a
	  grey tunic, pink mantle with green lining, a white veil and a golden
	  halo. Mary, significantly smaller, is seated on her lap, dressed in
	  blue, with an unidentified small golden object (an egg?) in her right
	  hand and the naked cross-nimbed Jesus seated sideways on her left
	  knee, reaching for the object. Yellow floor with geometrically
	  decorated tiles. Slender columns are flanking the scene and support
	  an arch of the same shape as the surrounding inner frame of burnished
	  gold. Foliated frame with blue and yellow acanthus, grapes and vine,
	  inhabited by David or Samson to the left, dressed in blue, orange and
	  white, with an orientalizing hat in pink and yellow, killing the
	  lion, a small grey owl top right, and a spoonbill lower right;
	  f. <locus>61r</locus>: illuminated and historiated initial (M) in burnished gold
	  with the Vistitation. Mary to the left in a mauve tunic and blue
	  mantle, holding an inscribed scroll. Elisabeth to the right in gredy
	  tunic and, mantle and white veil. Both are nimbed.  Foliated frame
	  with blue and yellow acanthus, small leaves and flowers in green and
	  pink, inhabited by a white bird on top, and a peacock in the right
	  margin;</p>

	<p>f. <locus>76v</locus>: full-page illumination of the Deposition. The dead,
	  cross-nimbed Christ in short beige loin-cloth is sinking into the
	  arms of the man to the left, dressed in blue with a pink purse, who
	  is climbing a ladder, while another man dressed in pink with blue
	  capuchon, kneeling by the foot of the cross, is removing the nail
	  from Christ's feet. Standing to the the right is St. Mary in pink
	  tunic and blue mantle, praying, and St. John in blue tunic and red
	  mantle. A road is leading through the landscape into the light blue
	  distant background. Foliated frame with blue and yellow acanthus,
	  small green leaves, cornflowers and golden stars, inhabited by a
	  white dove top left and a crane (?) in lower margin;</p>

	<p>f. <locus>77r</locus>: illuminated and historiated initial (H) in burnished gold
	  with the Man of sorrows standing in a landscape, dressed in short
	  loin-cloth and white mantle, hands tied together with a scourge, his
	  skin covered with small red wounds, his head crowned with
	  thorns. Foliated border with blue and yellow acanthus, blue grapes,
	  green vine and small golden stars, inhabited by a stork in the right
	  margin;</p>

	<p>f. <locus>86r</locus>: illuminated and historiated initial (H) in burnished gold
	  with the Annunciation. St. Mary is kneeling by a draped lectern
	  dressed in all blue turning her head towards the angel, who is
	  dressed in white with green wings, and holding an inscribed
	  scroll. Above the angel's head, the dove is flying amidst a fan of
	  golden rays. The interior walls are pink and the floor
	  yellow. Foliated border with blue and yellow acanthus, strawberries
	  and small golden stars, inhabited by a grey moorhen (?) and a crane
	  (?);</p>

	<p>f. <locus>113r</locus>: illuminated and historiated initial (H) in burnished gold
	  with the Coronation of the Virgin. The Father with grey hair and
	  beard, dressed in a grey tunic and blue mantle, and the Son with
	  brown hair and beard, dressed in a blue tunic and pink mantle, each
	  holding a sphere and together crowning the Virgin who is kneeling in
	  front of them, dressed in blue tunic and white mantle. The scene is
	  set in a grey church interior with yellow floor. Foliated frame with
	  blue and yellow acanthus, strawberries and small golden stars,
	  inhabited by a magpie;</p>

	<p>f. <locus>125r</locus>: illuminated and historiated initial (H) in burnished gold
	  with celebrating priest kneeling in front of the altar, wearing a
	  white alb and blue chasuble. Foliated frame with blue, yellow and
	  pink acanthus with orange and mauve gooseberries and small golden
	  stars, inhabited by a standing man, bottom right, in grey hoses and
	  pink jacket (badly damaged), shooting a green parrot, top right;</p>

	<p>f. <locus>213r</locus>: illuminated and historiated initial (M) in burnished gold
	  with  Jesus at the age of twelve teaching in the temple. Jesus seated
	  in the left part of the initial, dressed in mauve tunic, three
	  doctors in the right part of the initial, two seated, the third
	  standing, dressed in blue, green and grey with orange capuchon. The
	  scene is set in a grey temple interior with yellow floor. Foliated
	  frame with blue, yellow and pink acanthus, pink violets and small
	  golden stars, inhabited by a grey owl, top right, and a white swan
	  (?) (badly damaged) in the right margin;</p>

	<p>f. <locus>243r</locus>: illuminated and historiated initial (H) in burnished gold
	  with Christ carrying the cross. Christ dresseed in mauve tunic
	  standing in a landscape with the cross on his right shoulder facing
	  right. Foliated frame with blue, yellow and pink acanthus, pink
	  tulip-shaped flowers and small golden stars, inhabited by a grey owl
	  and a yellow finch;</p>

	<p>f. <locus>277v</locus>: full-page illumination of the Last judgement. Christ
	  dressed in a pink mantle with green lining and a golden clasp sits on
	  the rainbow with Earth as footpall, his right hand raised in
	  blessing, his left lowered in a rejecting gesture. Christ is flanked
	  by two trumpet-blowing angels clad in yellow with red or green
	  wings. Underneath in front are the kneeling figures of St. Mary in
	  pink tunic and blue mantle, to the left, and St. John in red tunic
	  and grey mantle, to the right, and in the background landscape, six
	  naked bodies raising from their open tombs. Foliated frame with blue
	  and yellow acanthus,small golden stars, green leaves, flowers in pink
	  and blue lilies, inhabited by two struggling men in the lower margin
	  with grey or orange hoses, black shoes, green or pink jackets and the
	  reverse colour on their hats, in the left margin a white bird and top
	  right a grey butterfly with grey and yellow wings;</p>

	<p>f. <locus>278r</locus>: illuminated and historiated initial (H) in burnished gold
	  with David praying. David, kneeling in a landscape is crowned and
	  dressed in red tunic and blue mantle. Foliated border with blue and
	  yellow acanthus, golden stars, small green leaves and flowers in
	  orange, inhabited by a white bird (damaged) in right margin and a
	  brown shoveler in upper margin;</p>

	<p>f. <locus>304v</locus>: full page illumination of the miracle of the Israelites
	  gathering manna. In a landscape with a road and a river between green
	  hills, trees and two towns fading towards the background in
	  athmospheric perspective, four men of different ages, a woman and a
	  child with baskets are occupied with gathering the manna which, in
	  the shape of consecrated wafers, fall from the partially gilt cloud
	  on top. Foliated frame decorated with blue and yellow acanthus,
	  grapes, vine and cornflowers, inhabited by two men in the lower
	  margin, dressed in grey hoses and shoes, blue or red  jackets and
	  the reverse colour on their hats, holding a ring or net between them,
	  and top left a peacock;</p>

	<p>f. <locus>315r</locus>: full-page illumination of a Sacra Conversazione with
	  St. Catherine of Alexandria, St. John the Baptist and St. John the
	  Evangelist. The badly damaged figure of St. Catherine dressed in blue
	  tunic and pink mantle with green lining holds in her right hand a
	  sword and in her left the wheel with iron spikes. St. John the
	  Baptist with white hair and beard is dressed in short brown tunic and
	  blue mantle, holding the lamb in his arms. St. John the Evangelist is
	  standing to the right dressed in blue tunic and red mantle, holding a
	  chalice. The scene is placed in an interior with yellow floor with
	  decorated tiles, blue roof following the shape of the golden frame
	  and pink walls with two windows, the left of which is open towards
	  the landscape. The rectangular area behind St. Catherine is gilt with
	  punched surface in rombic pattern. Foliated border with blue and
	  yellow acanthus, golden stars, green leaves and flowers in pink and
	  grey, inhabited by a white dog sitting on a grass-covered rock in the
	  lower margin, a white bird in the left margin and a butterfly with
	  wings in blue and ochre top right.</p>
	
	<p>Style: Although liturgically adopted for the use of Utrecht, the
	  manuscript show no characteristics of the Utrecht style, but closer
	  affinities with flemish products, above all from Bruges. Compare with
	  Den Haag, KB 76 F 30 made by the Master of the Small Eyes c. 1440 -
	  60 or with Den Haag, MMW 10 F13 from 1479 and Den Haag, KB, 135 G10,
	  made c 1460 for the Use of Utrecht by a follower of Willem Vrelant,
	  born in Utrecht, but active in Bruges.</p>

	<p>The historiated initials are generally of a higher quality than the
	  full-page miniatures, and closeley related to the workshop of Willem
	  Vrelant, though not to the master himself. Numerous features, such as
	  the treatment of folds, floor decoration, landscape and architecture
	  are identical in the miniatures and the initials, suggesting that the
	  whole extant illuminated decoration, with the exception of the frames
	  and borders, is the work of one artist, who probably was more
	  accustomed to working in the small format.</p>

	<p>Iconography: In the Anna selbdritt the feature of the gilt object in
	  the hand of the Virgin is tentatively interpreted as an egg. An egg
	  also occurs in the picture of the standing Madonna in St. Louis,
	  Washington University Library, Ms 3, where the motif is juxtaposed
	  with a peacock. In Medeltidshandskrift 52, the peacock has moved from
	  the actual image to the foliated frame of the facing page. Since the
	  St Louis manuscript has been attributed to the circle around Willem
	  Vrelant as well, the iconographical connection between the two
	  manuscripts corroborate the supposition of a common origin. The motif
	  prefigures the Passion and Resurrection  of Christ.</p>

	<p>The deposition includes Nicodemus, Joseph of Arimathea, St. Mary and
	  St. John.</p>

	<p>The composition of the Last Judgement with Christ seated on a
	  rainbow flanked by two trumpet-blowing angels, his right hand raised
	  in blessing, his left lowered in rejection, and the resurrection of
	  the dead between St. Mary and St. John, is repeated in numerous Books
	  of Hours, and is fully consistent with the Bruges tradition (cfr. the
	  above mentioned St Louis, Washington UL, Ms 3). The Judgement is
	  allegorically commented by the struggling men in the lower
	  margin.</p>

	<p>The miracle of manna shows consecrated wafers with images of the
	  Crucifixion, allegorically linking the scene of Exodus 16:14 ff. and
	  the striking of water from the rock (not present here) with the
	  typology of the Passion of Christ with the flesh and blood of the
	  communion.</p>

	<p>The saints in the Sacra Conversazione are identified by their
	  attributes, and the central position of St. Catherine strengthens the
	  attribution to Utrecht, although in fact the manuscript was produced
	  in Bruges.</p></decoNote>

    </decoration>

    <bindingDesc>
      <binding><p>Blind-tooled wine coloured fine grain goatskin binding; France (?) later half of the 19th century, flyleaf with date 1860. Rebacked, 20th century. Size: 160 x 125 x 68 mm.</p>
<p>Wine coloured fine grain goatskin binding over bevelled wooden boards with 20th century rebacking. Two engraved metal hook-clasp fastenings at fore-edge. Rounded spine. Hollow back with four false bands. Gilt title: <q>Livres d'Heures</q>, in second compartment and gilt date: <q>XIVme siècle</q>, at tail compartment of the back. Multicoloured stuck-on endbands. Edges gilt. Plain single flyleaves, made flyleaves and pastedowns of marbled paper. Wine coloured leather hinges. Green tassel. All along sewing on four cords.</p>
<p>The covers are blind-tooled into a large frame of multiple fillets and a repeated rectangular ornament in neo-gothic style, corner compartments with tooled angels. The central panel is divided into ogival compartments by a blind fillet and a stamp in renaissance style. The back is blind-tooled into four triple fillets panels with centre and corner stamps in 18th century style and two panels lettered in gilt.</p></binding></bindingDesc>

    <foliation><p>Foliated in pencil by modern cataloguer in upper right
	corner.</p></foliation>

    <additions><p>On f. i verso notes on the contents in French; on f. 327r:
	<q>Spiritus Sancti</q> 

	in the same hand as the note on f. 1r.</p></additions>

  </physDesc>
<history>
    <origin><p>The manuscript was produced in Bruges, for use in Utrecht,
	ab. 1460-80.</p></origin>

    <provenance><p>On f. ii recto: a note in French dated 10. Juin 1860, saying
      that the names of the owners of the manuscript on f. 1r: <name>Chara Suoellin</name>
      (?) et <name>A. Siemaszko</name>, are to be understood as the parents of the
      Lithuanian metropolitan <name>Joseph Siemaszko</name>.</p></provenance>

    <acquisition><p>In 1962 the manuscript was acquired by the University
	Library from the antiquiarian book dealer Boghallen in
	Copenhagen.</p></acquisition>

  </history>
<additional>
<adminInfo>
<recordHist>
<source>
<p>Catalogued by Margarete Andersson-Schmitt, the
	    manuscript description encoded in July of 2002 by Eva Nilsson
	    Nylander.</p>
</source>
<change>
<date rend="creation">2005-09-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record uploaded</item>
</change>
<change>
<date rend="revision">2005-09-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record revised</item>
</change>
</recordHist>
<remarks rend="audience">
<p>external</p>
</remarks>
</adminInfo>
</additional>
</msDescription>
