<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<msDescription id="Mh_64">
<msIdentifier>
<country reg="SE">Sweden</country>
<settlement>Lund</settlement>
<repository key="Mh">Lund University Library</repository>
<idno>Medeltidshandskrift 64</idno>
<altName type="database-identifier">scriptorium:Mh:589523:1138810197</altName>
</msIdentifier>
<msHeading>
<title>Miscellany</title> 
  <origPlace>Bohemia (?)</origPlace>
  <origDate notBefore="1450" notAfter="1500">15th century, second half</origDate>
  <textLang langKey="LAT">Latin</textLang>
    <note>The manuscript contains four different texts. It is bound with: Augustinus de Ancona, Summa de ecclesiastica potestate, printed in Lyon before 1480, and with Medeltidshandskrift 62 and 63.</note> 
  </msHeading>
<msContents>
<msItem n="1">
<locus from="1r" to="4v">ff. 1r-4v</locus>
<author>Alain de l'Isle</author>
<title>Doctrinale altum seu liber parabolarum</title>
<incipit>A Phoebe Phoebe lumen capit a sapiente insipiens</incipit>
<explicit>Nec superet qui te sic superare putat.</explicit>
<rubric type="final">Proverbiorum super probleumatum Alani liber explicit in lipit. in die undecimo milia virginum 1470 per studiosum M pellificis de Cadana</rubric>
<listBibl>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Doctrinale minus alias Liber parabolarum magistri Alani de Insulis</title>
<editor>de Wisch, Carolus</editor>
<title level="s">Patrologiae cursus completus. Series Latina, Migne, J.-P.</title>
<biblScope type="volume">210:0579</biblScope>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Parisiis</pubPlace>
<date>1844-64</date>
</imprint>
</bibl>
</listBibl>
</msItem>



<msItem n="2">
<locus from="5r" to="9r">ff. 5r-9r</locus>
<author>Adolphus of Vienna</author>
<title>Doligamus</title>
<incipit>Augurio docti fraudes didici</incipit>
<explicit>et post hanc metam det ei sedem bene letam iungeque solamen nunc dicat quilibet amen</explicit>
<rubric type="final">explicit doligamus per manum et non per pedes M Cadanensis in Lipsia (?) 1470 in profesto omnium sanctorum.</rubric>
<note>Nine fabulae of varying length concerning the deceitful conduct of women. The first 14 versers make up the acrosticon "Adolfus me fecit".</note>
<listBibl>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Adolfo di Vienna. Doligamus, gli inganni delle donne,</title>
<editor>a cura di Paola Casali.</editor>
<title level="s">Per Verba</title>
<biblScope type="volume">7</biblScope>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Firenze</pubPlace>
<date>1997</date>
</imprint>

<note>Casali lists 17 mss. none of which is Mh 64; cfr. also Yale, Beinecke
	    Rare Book and Manuscript Library MS 462 (ff. 2r-31r), Austria,
	    second half of 15th century, also not on Casali's list.</note>
</bibl>
</listBibl>
</msItem>

<msItem n="3">
<locus from="9r" to="11v">ff. 9r-11v</locus>
<author>Frovinus Cracoviensis</author>
<title>Antigameratus</title>
<incipit>Hos morum flores  si carpseris ut rosa flores</incipit>
<rubric type="final">Moralia Antigamerati canonici Cracoviensis qui etiam phisologum compilavit explicit feliciter in lipit.</rubric>
</msItem>

<msItem n="4">
<locus from="12r" to="12v">f. 12r-v</locus>
<title>Ortulus florum</title>
<incipit>cum nihil utilius humane credo saluti quam morum novisse modos et moribus uti</incipit>
<rubric type="final">finit ortulus florum p.m. Cadani</rubric>
</msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<support><p>Paper</p></support><extent>ff. 12, <dimensions><height>292</height><width>215</width></dimensions> mm.</extent>
<collation><p>1 quire: I: 12 (ff. 1-12).</p></collation>
<layout columns="2"><p>Ruled in ink; 2 columns (f. 9 traces of a third column (?) in cropped margin) with an intercolumnium of 25 mm.; written space: 230 x 150 mm.</p>
</layout>
<msWriting hands="1">
<handDesc script="Cursiva Recentior Libraria"><p>
One hand; Cursiva Recentior Libraria.</p></handDesc>
</msWriting> 
<decoration>
<decoNote><p>Red lombards. Drawings of scrolls in brown ink framing a few lines of text (ff. 4v, 9r, 11v, 12v) and small drawings of leaf-ornaments (ff. 6r, 7r).</p></decoNote>
</decoration>

<bindingDesc>
      <binding><p>Blind-tooled brown calfskin binding, contemporary with the
	  manuscript, restored back. Size: 300 x 220 x 80 mm.</p> 
	<p>Brown calfskin binding over square edged wooden boards (type [a],
	  cfr. Szirmai 1999 p. 219). Later recovering of the back late
	  19th or 20th century. The covering is worn, loose and partly missing
	  around endbands and at corners of the boards, the joint is cracked at
	  the lower part of the upper board. Two engraved hook-clasp fastenings
	  at fore-edge, engraving: ma[u or ri?]. Hook-clasp and leather strap of upper fastening missing. Lower anchor plate of later date, new nails. Worn
	  and partly damaged manuscript titles on paper labels in top
	  compartments and manuscript library code on paper in one of the lower
	  compartments of the back. Primary wound endbands with secondary
	  cross-stitched embroidery (type IV fig. 2.24, cfr. Szirmai 1999,
	  p. 208-209). The endbands are worn and the embroidery partly
	  missing. Trimmed edges, squares at head and tail. All along sewing on
	  three double split leather thongs laced through the boards. Some of
	  the bands are partly cracked at the joints of the upper
	  board. Endleaves missing.</p> 
	<p>The covers are blind-tooled with double fillets into a large frame
	  and central panel. The frame is stamped with an inscribed curved
	  ribbon tool into a partly irregular undulated and crossed pattern;
	  the corner compartments contain a large rosette placed in a square
	  made of the same ribbon tool. The central panel is stamped into
	  repeated ogival compartments with pomegranates in the centre. The
	  back is blind-tooled with double fillets next to the
	  bands.</p>
      </binding> 
    </bindingDesc>

<foliation><p>Foliated in pencil by modern cataloguer in upper right corner.</p></foliation>
<additions><p>Annotated in the margins throughout the manuscript.</p></additions>
</physDesc>
<history>
<origin><p>Leipa in Bohemia (?).</p></origin>
<provenance><p>There is a note on the first leaf of the printed book (with which the manuscript part is bound) saying that the book once belonged to a reformed Franciscan convent in Bolzano (?): <q>Conventu. Frum Min. reform. Bolsanensium</q>.</p>
<p>There is another note on the former front flyeaf, now a loose sheet, saying <q>Franciscus Borthanis me possidet)</q>.</p></provenance>
<acquisition><p>It is unknown how and when the book came to the	Library. There is a loose slip with a note in the hand of Per Ekström (librarian 1969-99) saying "okat. Bland Callmers kvarlåtenskap (1985)."</p></acquisition>
</history>
<additional>
<adminInfo>
<recordHist>
<source>
<p>Catalogued and encoded <date>in January of 2005</date> by <name>Eva Nilsson Nylander </name></p>
</source>
<change>
<date rend="creation">2006-02-01</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record uploaded</item>
</change>
<change>
<date rend="revision">2006-02-01</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record revised</item>
</change>
</recordHist>
<remarks rend="audience">
<p>external</p>
</remarks>
</adminInfo>
</additional>
</msDescription>
