<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<msDescription id="Mh_63">
<msIdentifier>
<country reg="SE">Sweden</country>
<settlement>Lund</settlement>
<repository key="Mh">Lund University Library</repository>
<idno>Medeltidshandskrift 63</idno>
<altName type="database-identifier">scriptorium:Mh:654719:1127809706</altName>
</msIdentifier>
<msHeading>
    <author>Boethius</author>
    <title type="uniform">De consolatione philosophiae</title> 
    <origPlace>France (?)</origPlace>
    <origDate notBefore="1450" notAfter="1500">15th century, later half</origDate> 
    <textLang langKey="LAT">Latin</textLang>
    <note>The manuscript is bound with: Augustinus de Ancona, Summa de
      ecclesiastica potestate, printed in Lyon before 1480, and with Medeltidshandskrift 62 and 64.</note> 
  </msHeading>
<msContents>
<msItem n="1">
<locus from="1r" to="47r">ff. 1r-47r</locus>
<author>Boethius, Anicius Manlius Torquatus Severinus</author> 
<title type="uniform">De consolatione philosophiae</title>
<incipit>Carmina qui quondam studio florente peregi</incipit>
<explicit>cum ante oculos agitis iudicis cuncta cernentis.</explicit>
<rubric type="final">Finit quintus et ultimus liber Boetii de consolatione philosophie.</rubric>
<note>Book 1: ff. 1r-8r; book 2: ff. 8v-17v; book 3: ff. 17v-32r; book 4: ff. 32r-41r; book 5: ff. 41v-47r; f. 47v: blank. </note>
<listBibl>
<bibl>
<title level="m">Anici Manli Severini Boethi De consolatione philosophiae libri quinque,</title>
<editor>quos denuo recognovit adnotationibus illustravit adiectis apparatu critico bibliographia indicibus biblioco et alageriano Adrianus A Forti Scuto; opus mortuo auctore ... edendum curavit Georgius D. Smith.</editor>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Londini,</pubPlace>
<date>1925.</date>
</imprint>
</bibl>
</listBibl>
</msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<support>
      <p>Paper</p>
    <watermarks>
	<p>Watermarks, close to but not identical with <ref>Briquet 4890</ref> and
	    <ref>Briquet 4893</ref> e.g. on f. 45.</p></watermarks></support>
    <extent>ff. 47, <dimensions><height>292</height><width>215</width></dimensions> mm.</extent>
<collation><p>4 quires: I: 12 (ff. 1-12), II: 12 (ff. 13-24), III: 12 (ff. 25-36), IV: 11 (ff. 37-47).</p></collation>
<layout columns="3"><p>Ruled in ink in three columns for text with commentary.</p>
</layout>
<msWriting>
<handDesc script="Cursiva Recentior Libraria"><p>
Several hands; main text: Cursiva Recentior Libraria; margins: hybrida currens.</p></handDesc>
</msWriting> 
<decoration>
<decoNote><p>Red lombards. Small drawing in left margin on f. <locus>13r</locus> in brown and red ink, concentric circles depicting an orb with a towered building on top. Brackets and marks in brown ink drawing in the shape of textiles or scrolls (ff. <locus>6v</locus>, <locus>8r</locus>, <locus>12v</locus>, <locus>15r</locus>, <locus>18v</locus>, <locus>22v</locus>, <locus>32r</locus>) and drawings of leaf-ornaments occasionally with red details (ff. <locus>8v</locus>, <locus>11r</locus>, <locus>11v</locus>, <locus>12r</locus>, <locus>13r</locus>, <locus>13v</locus>, <locus>14r</locus>, <locus>14v</locus>, <locus>15r</locus>, <locus>15v</locus>, <locus>17r</locus>, <locus>18r</locus>, <locus>19r</locus>, <locus>20r</locus>, <locus>22r</locus>, <locus>25r</locus>).</p></decoNote>
</decoration>

    <bindingDesc>
      <binding><p>Blind-tooled brown calfskin binding, contemporary with the
	  manuscript, restored back. Size: 300 x 220 x 80 mm.</p> 
	<p>Brown calfskin binding over square edged wooden boards (type [a],
	  cfr. Szirmai 1999 p. 219). Later recovering of the back late
	  19th or 20th century. The covering is worn, loose and partly missing
	  around endbands and at corners of the boards, the joint is cracked at
	  the lower part of the upper board. Two engraved hook-clasp fastenings
	  at fore-edge, engraving: ma[u or ri?]. Hook-clasp and leather strap of upper fastening missing. Lower anchor plate of later date, new nails. Worn
	  and partly damaged manuscript titles on paper labels in top
	  compartments and manuscript library code on paper in one of the lower
	  compartments of the back. Primary wound endbands with secondary
	  cross-stitched embroidery (type IV fig. 2.24, cfr. Szirmai 1999,
	  p. 208-209). The endbands are worn and the embroidery partly
	  missing. Trimmed edges, squares at head and tail. All along sewing on
	  three double split leather thongs laced through the boards. Some of
	  the bands are partly cracked at the joints of the upper
	  board. Endleaves missing.</p> 
	<p>The covers are blind-tooled with double fillets into a large frame
	  and central panel. The frame is stamped with an inscribed curved
	  ribbon tool into a partly irregular undulated and crossed pattern;
	  the corner compartments contain a large rosette placed in a square
	  made of the same ribbon tool. The central panel is stamped into
	  repeated ogival compartments with pomegranates in the centre. The
	  back is blind-tooled with double fillets next to the
	  bands.</p>
      </binding> 
    </bindingDesc>

<foliation><p>Foliated in pencil by modern cataloguer in upper right corner.</p></foliation>
<additions><p>Annotated. Pointing hands in the margins throughout the manuscript.</p></additions>
</physDesc>
<history>
    <origin><p>France (?), second half of 15th century.</p></origin>
<provenance><p>There is a note on the first leaf of the printed book (with which the manuscript part is bound) saying that the book once belonged to a reformed Franciscan convent in Bolzano: <q>Conventu. Frum Min. reform. Bolsanensium</q>.</p>
<p>There is another note on the former front flyeaf, now a loose sheet, saying <q>Franciscus Borthanis me possidet</q>.</p></provenance>
    <acquisition><p>It is unknown how and when the book came to the University library. There is a loose slip with a note in the hand of Per Ekström (librarian 1969-99) saying: <q>okat. Bland Callmers kvarlåtenskap (1985).</q></p></acquisition> 
  </history>
<additional>
<adminInfo>
<recordHist>
<source>
<p>Catalogued and encoded <date>in January of 2005</date> by <name>Eva Nilsson Nylander </name></p>
</source>
<change>
<date rend="creation">2005-09-27</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record uploaded</item>
</change>
<change>
<date rend="revision">2005-09-27</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record revised</item>
</change>
</recordHist>
<remarks rend="audience">
<p>external</p>
</remarks>
</adminInfo>
</additional>
</msDescription>
