<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<msDescription id="Mh_60">
<msIdentifier>
<country reg="SE">Sweden</country>
<settlement>Lund</settlement>
<repository key="Mh">Lund University Library</repository>
<idno>Medeltidshandskrift 60</idno>
<altName type="database-identifier">scriptorium:Mh:515669:1137078368</altName>
</msIdentifier>
<msHeading>
    <title lang="ENG">Epistulary</title> 
    <origPlace>Germany (?)</origPlace>
    <origDate notBefore="1200" notAfter="1225">13th century, early</origDate>
    <textLang langKey="LAT">Latin</textLang>
  </msHeading>
<msContents>
<msItem n="1" defective="yes">
<locus from="1r" to="20v">ff. 1r-20v</locus>
<title type="uniform">Epistulary</title>
<incipit defective="yes">vos karissimi quia unus dies apud Dominum sicut mille anni</incipit>
<explicit defective="yes">omnis qui praecedit et non permanet in doctrina Christi</explicit>
<note>The text starts defectively in 2 Peter 3:8; at ff. 3r-19v: 1 John 1-5; the text ends defectively at f. 20v in 2 John 1:9.</note>
</msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
    <support><p>Parchment.</p></support>
    <extent>ff. 20<dimensions>
	<height>260</height><width>175</width></dimensions>mm. 
    </extent>
<collation><p>3 quires: I: 8 (ff. 1-8), II: 4 (ff. 9-12), III: 8 (ff. 13-20). Quire signatures at f. 8v (vii), f. 12v (viii) and f. 20v (ix).</p></collation>
<layout columns="3" writtenLines="32"><p>Pricking in upper, lower and outer margin, ruled in ink; central column: 32 ruled lines, 16 written; side columns: 32 rules and written lines.</p></layout>
<msWriting hands="1">
<handDesc script="Gothic book hand"><p>
Gothic book hand in three sizes for text, marginal gloss and interlinear gloss. The manuscript is unfinished; marginal gloss ends at f. 16r and interlinerar gloss ends at f. 17v.</p></handDesc>
</msWriting> 

    <decoration>
      <decoNote><p>Alternating red and blue intials with pen flourishes in the
	  opposite colour. Two larger initials with extensive pen flourishes,
	  two lines in height, on f. <locus>3r</locus>, <locus>19v</locus>; the
	  others, one line in height, are divided in two groups, the first of
	  which show extended pen flourishes (f. <locus>1v</locus>,
	  <locus>2v</locus>, <locus>5v</locus>, <locus>6v</locus>,
	  <locus>9r</locus>, <locus>10v</locus>, <locus>11v</locus>,
	  <locus>12r</locus>, <locus>13v</locus>, <locus>14v</locus>,
	  <locus>15r</locus>, <locus>15v</locus>, <locus>16r</locus>,
	  <locus>18r</locus>, <locus>18v</locus>) the decoration of the
	  remaining being more restricted.</p> 

	<p>Detailed description:
	  <list>
	    <item>f. <locus>3r</locus>: Initial Q in blue with
	      filling consisting of S curling spirals in red with blue details,
	      bordure decoration and pen flourishes in red with minute flower
	      ornaments on the tail;</item>
	    
	    <item>f. <locus>19v</locus>: Initial S in blue with decorative
	      filling somewhere between bordure and filigranated decoration in
	      red with blue circular details, and pen flourishes in blue and
	      red extended into the lower margin.</item>
	  </list>
	</p>
      </decoNote> 
    </decoration>

    <bindingDesc>
      <binding><p>Whittawed and reversed leather binding, Romanesque boards
	  contemporary the with manuscript, covering of reversed leather
	  possibly later (cfr. Szirmai 1999 pp. 140 sqq, p. 225). Restored
	  back, 20th century. Size: 262 x 192 x 28 mm.</p> 
	<p>Whittawed and reversed leather binding over thick rounded Romanesque
	  oak boards. Leather covering of the back restored. Two long-strap
	  fastenings at fore-edge, former hasp missing, straps new. Holes from
	  chain attachment at the top of the lower cover. Tight back with three
	  raised bands. Remnants of title labels at the top part of the upper
	  cover. Endbands missing. Trimmed edges. No squares. Pastedowns of
	  parchment. Front pastedown with restorations. Back pastedown partly
	  defect from tearing showing pieces of manuscript waste of the lower
	  board. All along sewing on three double thongs laced through the
	  boards. Thongs later cut flush with the spine and restored at the
	  joint of the upper board.</p>
      </binding> 
    </bindingDesc>
<foliation><p>The manuscript is foliated by modern cataloguer in pencil in upper right corner of recto side of the leaves. </p></foliation>
<additions><p>Notes at ff. <locus>12r</locus>, <locus>18v</locus> and <locus>20v</locus>; erased notes at ff. <locus>2v</locus>, <locus>15v</locus>,  modern marginal notes in pencil at ff. <locus>1r</locus>, <locus>3r</locus>, <locus>19v</locus>.</p></additions>

  </physDesc>
<history>
<origin><p/></origin>
<acquisition><p>The manuscript, bought in Heidelberg in 1969, was donated to the University library in 1975 by Gunlög Steidler-Ivarsson, Landskrona.</p></acquisition>
</history>
<additional>
<adminInfo>
<recordHist>
<source/>
<change>
<date rend="creation">2006-01-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record uploaded</item>
</change>
<change>
<date rend="revision">2006-01-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record revised</item>
</change>
</recordHist>
</adminInfo>
</additional>
</msDescription>
