<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<msDescription id="Mh_9">
<msIdentifier>
<country reg="SE">Sweden</country>
<settlement>Lund</settlement>
<repository key="Mh">Lund University Library</repository>
<idno>Medeltidshandskrift 9</idno>
<altName type="former shelfmark">Bibl. Ms. H. L. a) 4:o, N:o 15</altName>
<altName type="former shelfmark">Bibl. Ant. 7.30, N:o 15</altName>
<altName lang="LAT" type="nickname">Liber decretalium minor</altName>
<altName type="database-identifier">scriptorium:Mh:976887:1120120903</altName>
</msIdentifier>
<msHeading>
  <title lang="ENG">Decretals</title> 
  <origPlace>France (Paris?)</origPlace>
  <origDate notBefore="1275" notAfter="1300">13th century, last quarter (c. 1280)</origDate>
  <textLang langKey="LAT">Latin</textLang>
 </msHeading>
<msContents>
<msItem n="1">
<locus from="1r" to="194r">ff. 1r-194r</locus>
<title type="uniform">Liber extra</title>
<incipit defective="yes">quatenus, si ita esse constiterit, revocatis in statum pristinum </incipit>
<explicit>Indignum est et a Romanae ecclesiae consuetudine alienum, ut pro spiritualibus facere quis homagium compellatur.</explicit>
<rubric type="final">Explicit liber quintus decretalium</rubric>
<note><p>The book has been taken apart and restored and leaves have been lost and put together incorrectly.</p>
<p>Liber I begins defectively on f. 1r with the end of tit. 3, cap. 12.</p>
<p>Liber II begins defectively on f. 53r with the beginning of tit. 38, cap. 11.</p>
<p>Liber III begins on f. 70r (cf. decoradetd intitial).</p>
<p>Liber IV begins on f. 124v (cf. decoradetd intitial).</p>
<p>Liber V begins defectively on f. 143 in the middle of tit. 1, cap. 10.</p></note>
</msItem>

<msItem n="2">
<locus from="194v" to="196v">ff. 194v-196v</locus>
<!--title type="uniform">???/Gamla katalogen säger: Novellae of Innocence IV</title-->
<!--rubric></rubric-->
<!--incipit></incipit-->
<!--incipit defective="yes"></incipit-->
<note><!--p>Vad är det för texter på ff. 194r-196v??
Jag har skrivit till Anders Winroth 28 juni 2005.
Han är out of office till den 10 juli.</p--></note>
</msItem>

<msItem n="3">
<locus from="197r" to="204v">ff. 197r-204v</locus>
<title type="uniform">Liber sextus</title>
<incipit defective="yes">ganei sui excommunicationis sententiam ex aliqua rationabili causa profert</incipit>
<explicit defective="yes">pro utilitate communi contra iuris asperitatem exe</explicit>
<note><p>This last quire is presumably from another, slightly later, book.</p>
<p>The text begins defectively in the middle of Liber I, tit. 13, cap. 1 and ends in in Liber II, tit. 14, cap. 3.</p></note>
</msItem>

</msContents>
<physDesc>
  <support><p>Parchment</p></support>
  <extent>ff. ii + 206 + ii,<dimensions><height>130</height><width>85</width></dimensions>mm.</extent>
<collation><p>The collation is disturbed, probably in connection with a restauration. 12 quires: I: 16 (ff. 1-16); II: 4 (ff. 17-20); III: 16 (ff. 21-36); IV: 16 (ff. 37-52); V: 24 (ff. 52-76); VI: 24 (ff. 77-100); VII: 18 (ff. 101-118); VIII: 24 (ff. 119-142); IX: 19 (ff. 142-160); X: 24 (ff. 161-184); XI: 12(ff. 185-196); XII: 12 (ff. 197-204).</p></collation>
<layout columns="2" writtenLines="44"><p>Ruled in ink, two columns with an intercolumnium of 5 mm., 44 written lines, written space: 95 x 60 mm.; cropped margins with loss of text.</p></layout>
<msWriting hands="2">
<handDesc script="Textualis"><p>A small Textualis ("pearl script"). Two hands: hand 1 has written everything except f. 35b, f. 196 and maybe also the last quire, ff. 197-204, where the parchment is also of a different  quality.</p></handDesc></msWriting> 

    <decoration>
      <decoNote><p>The preserved decoration consists of two historiated and
	  illuminated initials, described below, and 1590 pen flourished
	  initials alternating in blue and red with flourishes in the opposite
	  colour. In the main portion of the text (ff. 1-195) the initials are
	  placed in the margin, next to the written text, with flourishes
	  extending vertically along the margins, while in the last part, the
	  initials are placed in the reserved spaces in the written text, with
	  flourishes restricted to shorter sprouts.</p> 
	<p>Detailed description:
	  <list>
	    <item>f. <locus>70r</locus>: An illuminated and
	      historiated initial U, 18 x 24 mm, in pink decorated with circles
	      and crosses in white, inscribed in a square with red frame and
	      blue background embellished by small gilt roundels and thin white
	      tracery. The upper left serif extends into a leaf ornament in
	      blue with gilt roundes, the lower right serif into a small green
	      leaf ornament. The inner space of the initial is inhabited by
	      three clercs in front of an altar. The one to the left is dressed
	      in blue with a belt in orange, the one in the middle has a white
	      alb and a blue dalmatic with  silver lining, the one to the right
	      in with alb with gilt rubra and blue chausuble with silver
	      lining. To the right of him a blue altar with orange pediment and
	      white mortar, on which stands a veiled silver chalice. The
	      backgrond is mauve with minute white dots;
	    </item>
	    <item>f. <locus>122r</locus>: A crude drawing in brown ink of a
	      human face in profile;</item>
	    <item>f. <locus>124v</locus>: An illuminated and historiated
	      initial D, 23 X 33 mm, in blue with circles and dotted undy
	      decoration in white and serifs ending in leaf ornaments in pink
	      and orange. The letter is inscribed in a square with light green
	      frame and pink backround withgilt roundels and thin white
	      tracery. The inner space of the initial is inhabited by a bishop
	      clad in white alb with gilt rubra, chausuble in mauve with gilt
	      lining and with white mitre and staff. At his right side stands a
	      crowned king with light green tunic and dark brown mantle, and at
	      his left stands a slender woman dressed in red. These two reach
	      their right hands to each other. The background is blue with
	      minute white dots.</item>
	  </list>
	</p> 
	<p>Style: The illuminated initials are minutely executed by the same
	  accomplished artist, working in the parisian tradition of e.g. the
	  workshop of Johannes Grusch. Although the small size and relative
	  simplicity of the motifs makes a strong attribution difficult at this
	  point, Paris seems the most plausible place of origin. The pen
	  flourished initials are divided between three artists. The slender
	  and narrow pen flourished initials in the main portion of the
	  manuscript (ff. <locus from="1r" to="195">1r-195v</locus>) are
	  executed around 1270 by artist A, the 
	  last initial on f. <locus>195v</locus> and the two on
	  f. <locus>196v</locus>, close in general appearance, but less
	  accomplished, are executed by artist B, while the remaining, rounder
	  and less detailed and close in style to the initials in Mh 10, are
	  executed by artist C towards the end of the century.</p> 
	<p>Iconography: The scene with the three clerks on
	  f. <locus>70r</locus> depicts the consecration of the wine as a
	  representative illustration of purely ecclesiastic matter as
	  suggested by the text itself. The betrothal on f. <locus>124v</locus>
	  illustrates the canonic view on marriage as a sacrament, actively
	  involving the blessing of the Church, rather than an act of consensus
	  between the two parties alone.</p>
      </decoNote> 
    </decoration>

    <bindingDesc>
      <binding>
	<p>Parchment binding with fore-edge yapps, Sweden, Lund 17th or 18th
	  century. Size: 136 x 90 x 34 mm.</p> 
	<p>Parchment binding over pasteboards with fore-edge yapps. Hollow
	  back. Manuscript title in sepia ink. Stuck-on white and blue linen
	  endbands embroidered on parchment tape laced through the
	  covers. Trimmed edges, manuscript losses at headmargin. Two plain
	  flyleaves and pastedowns of paper. On front pastedown several notes and former shelf marks (see above). All along sewing on three
	  parchment tapes laced through the covers. Textblock
	  restored.</p>
      </binding>
    </bindingDesc>
<foliation><p>The ms. is foliated  (1-204, + 35b, 145a) in pencil in upper right corner by 19th century librarian August Palm. In several occasions he has indicated where leaves, in connection with a rebinding, have been put in the wrong order: f. 2 (15), f. 15 (2), f. 17 (20), f. 18 (19), f. 19 (18), f. 20 (17).</p></foliation><additions><p>On front pastedown notes on the contents of the book and several former shelfmarks. On f. i recto a loose slip of paper glued to the leaf with a note saying <q>Decretales Gregor. [et9 nove. decr. (Innocentii). Från 1200-talets senare hälft.</q> All through the ms. there are marginal notes in pencil in the minute hand of August Palm, librarian at the University library 1856-1907, identifying the different parts of the text.</p></additions><condition><p>Lower margin of f. 117 has been cut out. The upper margin is cropped all through the book.</p></condition>
  </physDesc>
<history>
<origin><p>France (Paris), ab. 1270.</p></origin>
<provenance><p>In the will of archdeacon Haagen, probably identical to one
Haagen mentioned in 1253 (DD, II, 1:120 &amp; 122), dated 1 August
1283 (Diplomatarium Danicum II, 3, 73) a collection of decretals was
given to dean Andreas. He also gave a Breviary and a collection of
Danish law books, as well as money to buy a missal. This could possibly refer to Mh 9.</p></provenance>
<acquisition><p>The manuscript entered the library in 1671 when the chapter
was formally reorganized, or dissolved, and its manuscripts were
transferred to the University library.</p></acquisition> 
  </history>
<additional>
<adminInfo>
<recordHist>
<change>
<date rend="creation">2005-06-30</date>
<respStmt>
<name>eva</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Record uploaded</item>
</change>
<change>
<date rend="revision">2005-06-30</date>
<respStmt>
<name/>
</respStmt>
<item>Record revised</item>
</change>
</recordHist>
<remarks rend="audience">
<p>external</p>
</remarks>
</adminInfo>
<listBibl>
      <bibl>
	<author>Pellegrin, E.</author>
	<title level="a">Manuscrits d'auteurs latins de l'époque classique
	  conservés dans les bibliothèques publiques de
	  Suède</title>

	<title level="j">Bulletin d'information de l'institut de recherches et
	  d'histoire des texts</title>

      <biblScope type="volume">3 (1954)</biblScope>
      <imprint>
	<date>1955</date>
      </imprint>
      <biblScope type="pages">pp. 7-32 (esp. pp. 28-31)</biblScope>
    </bibl>
  </listBibl>
</additional>
</msDescription>
